<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The novells of Gio. Francesco Loredano a nobleman of Venice. Translated for diversion into English.</title>
            <author>Loredano, Giovanni Francesco, 1607-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217734</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33822</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33822)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1993:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The novells of Gio. Francesco Loredano a nobleman of Venice. Translated for diversion into English.</title>
                  <author>Loredano, Giovanni Francesco, 1607-1661.</author>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>153, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Fox at the Star, and Henry Lord at the Duke of Monmouth in Westminster-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33822:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NOVELLS OF <hi>Gio. Franceſco Loredano,</hi> A NOBLEMAN OF VENICE. <hi>Tranſlated for diverſion into</hi> Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Fox</hi> at the Star, and <hi>Henry Lord</hi> at the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall. 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33822:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33822:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33822:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33822:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>GIO. BATTISTA F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SCONI</hi> TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THeſe <hi>Novels</hi> being careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcattered up and down, I thought it my duty dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to collect them into one Volume. Flowers bound up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a Poſie do make a much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhew than when they lye ſtrowed abroad here and there. Accept, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader, the Stories of a Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that knows alſo how to compoſe Hiſtories. The Book would have been much bigger, if the Author, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imploy'd in more important Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, had not refus'd to gratifie my Requeſt. May you live free from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralling Paſſions, which is as much as to ſay happy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33822:4"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HAving pleas'd my ſelf, for ſome little time in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating, I thought good to give others an hour or two's diverſion in reading of theſe Amorous Diſcourſes. If I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted any thing from the worth of my Author, by coming ſhort of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteneſs of his Style; I have alſo added ſomething to his praiſe, by publiſhing his Work to thoſe that underſtand no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Language. I beg your acceptance, and bid you farewel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33822:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div n="1" type="novel">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aleria</hi> a moſt beautiful Lady, being not in the leaſt moved by the many Courtſhips and Addreſſes of the Marqueſs <hi>Arderico,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes inclined to love him, only for that he is highly commended by her Husband. His good word effects that which all the ſollicitations and ſervices of the other could not do. The Marqueſs on the contrary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acquainted herewith, upon the very point of enjoying the fruits of his love, doth generouſly quit his pretenſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVEL</hi> I.</head>
               <p>AMong other the Ladies, in the famous City of <hi>Vicenza,</hi> which did raviſh both the eyes and hearts of all Men, the beauty of <hi>Aleria</hi> (of the Noble Houſe of the Counts of <hi>Maloſi</hi>) did ſo far exceed that of the reſt, that it left no room neither for detraction nor amendment. The faireſt faces gave
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33822:5"/>
place to that aſpect which would have been thought Divine, if by her Courtly Carriage ſhe had not diſcovered ſome graceful Tracts of Humanity.</p>
               <p>This Lady (who was Courted by thoſe alſo that deſpaired of obtaining her) yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience only to thoſe affections which obliged her to prefer true merit, did conſent to be Married to the Count of <hi>Sanca Croce;</hi> a Gentlemen both for Birth and Vertue inferiour to none. He had no Quality that was not amiable, nor any thing in him that was not admirable. The Wedding was celebrated with that ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor which was befitting their Noble Eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate. Thoſe who in the general Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did bury their particular conſolation, did not refrain from being preſent at this Solemnity, although in others rejoycing, they ſaw cauſe of mourning. Muſick and dancing, which have power to raviſh even thoſe hearts that are moſt deeply affected with Melancholy, could not aſſwage the grief of their minds, who, together with the beauty of <hi>Aleria,</hi> did loſe the hopes of their lives. Yet many, by their dextrous ingenuity, making a vertue of neceſſity, not being able to ſubdue their affection, did direct it to other Women. Others
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33822:5"/>
knowing their eyes to have been the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of letting in love to their hearts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to deprive them of ſuch their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency, by withdrawing them from their beloved object. They fled away from that Climate, wherein the Sun did not ſhine but in favour of others. Some following the rules of him that taught the Remedy of Love, ſet themſelves to ſpy faults in that Face which, being of heavenly beauty, could not be thought exempt from Clouds. Onely <hi>Arderico</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Caſtel No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> raiſing his hopes above the impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Enterpriſe, found that the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of this day had made his love more ardent; whilſt others had thereby applied remedies to their paſſion. He, being as I believe, in an extaſie of grief, was aſſiſting to all the Offices of that day; imitating thoſe fooliſh Flies, which ſo they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the light of a Candle, do not care if they burn themſelves in its flame. He endur'd his torment with ſo much impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, that the leaſt effect of his diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amazement was the forgetting of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. The Feaſt being over he found new fuel added to his fire. The abſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did not extinguiſh, but foment his flames. Wretched <hi>Arderico</hi> felt his love
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33822:6"/>
grow the hotter, for being farther from the refreſhing beauties of <hi>Aleria.</hi> She, on the contrary, did give ſuch pure demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of her zealous affection to her Husband, that all hope, except that of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derico</hi>'s, which was devoted to obſtinacy, would have turn'd to deſpair. But he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, loving ſo much the more for his being leſs beloved, let ſlip no occaſion of diſcovering to her his diſeaſe. His eyes were continually fixed upon her, he aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her with ſighs, and ask'd pity of her by his looks; in ſum, he waiting on her in all places, and courting her at all Balls, there fell out no accident which he did not ſignalize, either, by ſome demonſtration of obſequiouſneſs, or teſtimony of his aff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ection. Yet <hi>Aleria,</hi> either not believing, or not caring to be belov'd, never lookt upon him but with an indifferent eye. And although the rules of good manners did oblige, her to yield to him in dancing, and to correſpond with him in ſaluting; yet ſhe did it without the leaſt acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his affection. <hi>Arderico</hi> having no other means to inſinuate his love into the mind of <hi>Aleria,</hi> had recourſe to his Pen; and with much ado, his tears inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixing with the Ink, and defacing his Writing, he formed this Letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33822:6"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Fair Lady,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I ſhould think I did deſerve the rigors of your diſdain for diſcovering my affection, if I did not know that every heart ſtands obliged to love things that are divine. The rays of your beauty have kindled ſo great a fire in my breaſt, that I ſhould believe the hiding it to be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an effect of ſtupidity than of Vertue. <hi>Aleria</hi> I love you, and if the ties of Love were ſo powerful as thoſe of Religion, I would ſay I adore you. But what my Pen conceals will be made manifeſt in my ſoul, if you pleaſe not to diſdain the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt humble Servant <hi>Arderico.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Having ſealed the Letter, he bethought him of the beſt way how to convey it ſafe into the hands of <hi>Aleria.</hi> Her Servants, though gained by the exceſſes of his Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, yet durſt not attempt the affections of a Miſtriſs ſo chaſt, that ſhe gave not the leaſt motive for temptation. To make uſe of other perſons he thought it both ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous &amp; dangerous; wherefore he reſolv'd himſelf to be the Porter. He pitch'd upon a day when ſhe was at Church, perhaps
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33822:7"/>
more adored than adoring. And coming as near to her as well he could, deceiving the ſuſpicion and obſervation of many, whilſt <hi>Aleria</hi> was intent upon her mental Devotions, he conveyed the Billet into her Prayer-Book, which by chance ſhe had laid behind her. There was not any one that perceived it. <hi>Aleria</hi> her ſelf, when ſhe took up her Book again, was not at firſt aware of it. She no ſooner ſaw it but ſhe was ſurpriz'd with a bluſh, being more angry with her ſelf for having given others an occaſion to tempt her, than diſpleaſed for having been tempted. This prudent Lady knew very well that ſhe could not be called chaſt, if ſhe did not reſiſt the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Lovers. Whoſoever is chaſt meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for neceſſity, I think her unworthy of that Character. <hi>Aleria</hi> having overcome thoſe confuſions which left the marks of Vermilion in her Cheeks, and ſtifled that curioſity which is ſo natural unto Women, when ſhe ſaw her time, tore the Letter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a thouſand pieces, as if that had been guilty of the faults of him that wrote it. <hi>Arderico</hi> feeling his own heart rent in the tearing of that Paper, did deſpair of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the future, any means to certifie his love unto her. He was really confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33822:7"/>
at her proceedings, who being beloved, did not only not accept thereof, but gave out ſigns that ſhe knew not of it. He, poor man, continued in his ſlavery, being ſo much the more unhappy, by how much the leſs proſpect he had of the hopes of any reward. It happen'd that <hi>Aleria,</hi> in company of her Husband went into the Country for to enjoy that ſeaſon of the Year which, bearing more fruits than any other, ſeemeth by its deliciouſneſs greatly to excite the appetites of Men. <hi>Arderico,</hi> who was the Eliotrope of this Sun, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, not without hopes that the retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Country would afford him that which the divertiſements of the City had deny'd him; and then he preſum'd that he could more eaſily bribe the Country People, for that the minds of Men, the baſer they are, the ſooner they are corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He was ſcarce come thither, but he began to ſurround the houſe of <hi>Aleria,</hi> with pretence of ſpreading Nets for Birds and hunting of Wild Beaſts, whilſt his heart was indeed entangled in the ſnares of Love, and continually tormented with the ſence of his Paſſion. One day, either acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally or willingly, he enter'd her Palace, upon colour of looking for a Falcon that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33822:8"/>
was fled from off his Fiſt. The Count of S. <hi>Croce, Aleria's</hi> Husband, receiv'd him with thoſe demonſtrations of kindneſs and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility which are uſual among Gentlemen; and having commanded his Servants that they ſhould follow the Hawk, he carried <hi>Arderico</hi> in to ſee his Wife. I know not how to expreſs this encounter, which may better be conceived by imagination. Let it ſuffice that <hi>Arderico</hi> did bluſh, look pale, and was affected both with heat and cold at one and the ſame time. He was, by courteous invitation, conſtrained to taſt of ſome fruits, whilſt that his eyes feeding on their beloved beauties, all other Meats were diſtaſtful unto him. At length hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing recovered his Falcon, after many obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Complements paſſed, he departed a more paſſionate Lover than when he came thither. He never had ſeen <hi>Aleria</hi> look more favourably, nor had ever received ſo much courteſie from her as at that time. <hi>Aleria</hi> on the other ſide, being very well ſatisfied with the good Behaviour of <hi>Arde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico,</hi> ask'd her Husband what the name of that Gentleman was whom he had ſo kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained. The Count ſmiled at this demand, and afterwards replied, Do not you know <hi>Arderico</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Caſtel
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33822:8"/>
Novo?</hi> Is it poſſible that you only ſhould be blind, and not ſee the Sun ſhine? Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me if it ſeem ſtrange that you ſhould not come to the knowledge of ſo Worthy a Man. I muſt needs think that your heart is perverted, or your ſoul degenerated when you have not had eyes to ſee the Worth of ſo conſpicuous a Gentleman. All perfections which are deſired in others, are fulfilled in him. By his unerring Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he cauſeth admiration, even in thoſe that hate him. With a free and diſinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted Courage he always take part with that which is juſt. By the modeſty of his deportment he hath overcome all envy. In ſhort, he is inferiour to none in Arms, no one ſuperiour to him in Learning, and as to his Nobility he hath no equal. He hath all the advantages both of Mind and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; neither is there any Lady ſo fair in <hi>Vicenza,</hi> that would not eſteem her ſelf ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fortunate if ſhe were honoured but with one look from this Noble Gentleman. And pray do not you contrariwiſe, neglect the knowledge of others excellencies, if you vvould not have me think you to be of a poor and mean ſpirit. <hi>Aleria</hi> excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelf very coldly, repenting vvithin her ſelf that ſhe had ſo long ſlighted the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33822:9"/>
ſervice of a Man, who for his ſingular good qualities did deſerve to be loved above all others. Shee, being fully ſatisfied with theſe Encomiums, grew ſo paſſionately in love with <hi>Arderico,</hi> that ſhe turn'd wholly Rebel to the Laws of Honeſty. That ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty which could not be ſubdued by a continual obſequiouſneſs; which reſiſted the perſuaſions of Servants, the flatteries of Lovers, the aſſaults of Senſuality, and the powers of Love, was proſtituted to the candid Speech and betrayed by the tongue of him that ought to have guarded it. That heart that could not be overcome by the eyes, was vanquiſhed by the ears. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore hurried by that vehemency which does uſually agitate the ſoul of a Lover, (the Count her Husband being gone to <hi>Vicenza</hi> about earneſt buſineſs) ſhe wrote a Letter in manner following, to the Marqueſs <hi>Arderico.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>If the demonſtrations of your affection do not deceive the ardency of my deſires, I am reſolv'd to run the hazard of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with your ſatisfaction. I blame my ſelf for taking up ſo precipitous a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, but I deſire not to be innocent,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33822:9"/>
when by being faulty I become yours. I would ſay more, but Love being a Child knows not how to ſpeak. About three hours within night I will expect your coming to my Lodgings by way of the Garden-gate which you ſhall find on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhut to. Let me receive a kind anſwer, who am</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt devoted Servant <hi>Aleria.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>She ſent this Letter by a Maiden who was obliged to Fidelity by her exceſſive Liberality. This Maid preſented it to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derico,</hi> who, believing it to be a Dream, could not reſolve what anſwer to give; at laſt, taking Pen and Paper, he wrote as followeth:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Dear Aleria,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I would thank you for that kindneſs which hath enriched my poor hopes, if divine favours did not oblige one rather to a ſilent acknowledgment, than to open thankfulneſs. I will come according to your appointment, about the third hour of the night, to ſacrifice my heart unto you. I ſhall gladly perform this duty by night, becauſe all things ſeeming great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the night time, I may then perhaps
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33822:10"/>
ſeem better unto you than really I am: and then, in the dark, you cannot ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcern the nakedneſs of my deſerts. In the mean time pleaſe to preſerve me as I am, </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt obliged and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Servant,
<hi>Arderico.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſent away the Letter he began to long for the night with ſuch amorous dotages as are wont to tyrannize over Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. He let not one moment of the hour appointed ſlip, before he was at the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Aleria.</hi> Their complements and endearments are referred to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe who have been the ſubjects of the like entertainment. <hi>Aleria</hi> was already gotten into Bed, expecting to give vent in amorous embraces, to thoſe paſſions which do torment the minds of Lovers. <hi>Arderico</hi> being abaſhed to ſee himſelf prevented, began to ſtrip himſelf with all diligence. Whilſt with an amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous impatience he was pulling off his Clothes, he askt <hi>Aleria</hi> the reaſon, why after ſo many ſlightings of the proofs of his affection, ſhe had ſo ſuddenly conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to his deſires, at a time when he was aſſigning over all his pretenſions unto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33822:10"/>
deſperation. My Love, anſwered <hi>Aleria,</hi> the extraordinary Character of your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo lively repreſented to me by my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, hath ſo entirely ſubdued my Spirit, that I did not believe I could live without you; and here ſhe repeated to him all that her Husband had ſaid. Well then, ſaid <hi>Arderico,</hi> had neither my love, nor my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice any power to win your heart, if the Voice of the Count your Husband, ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth my praiſes, had not charmed your Soul? It is even ſo replied <hi>Aleria.</hi> God forbid, added <hi>Arderico,</hi> putting on his Clothes again, that I ſhould injure him, who by ſuch generous expreſſions of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour towards me, doth Violate the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity of the moſt noble Woman. Pardon me <hi>Aleria,</hi> I cannot ſerve you to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of his Honour who by his Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums ſo much advanceth the merit of my Quality. In ſaying ſo, he went haſtily out of doors, by this action teaching men the true Worth of Gentility; Husbands that they ought not to ſpeak too much in praiſe of other men to their Wives; and preſcribing unto Women, more eſpecialy to thoſe that are Married, not to run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of ſetling their affections on a Man who may be changed every moment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="novel">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33822:11"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epidorus</hi> a young man of <hi>Florence,</hi> falls unwarily in Love with a Maſquerade that he did not know, and believing her to be a Noble Lady called <hi>Leena,</hi> he very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſues for love unto her. Having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his Suit, whilſt he thinks he enjoys her, he finds himſelf encircled within the Arms of a Chambermaid whom, in his own defence he is forced to Marry.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVEL</hi> II.</head>
               <p>THere came to <hi>Venice,</hi> for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create himſelf in time of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neval, Epidorus</hi> a young <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine,</hi> of a very mean Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, but who had, by the avarice of his Father, gotten to himſelf ſome ſort of Reputation. This young Man, by the Death of his Progenitors, was poſſeſſed of ſo great an Eſtate, that it gave not only light to the obſcurity of his Birth, but made him alſo ambitious of enjoying thoſe pleaſures which are oftentimes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33822:11"/>
ſought after by the greateſt Perſonages. There was no Feaſt, Play, nor Publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling in <hi>Venice,</hi> unto which he would not go. One Evening at a Ball he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf love-ſtricken by an imaginary beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The ſtately Gate and rich Attire of a Maſquerade did ſo bewitch his fancy, that he confeſſed himſelf her Lover before he could ſee her face. Neither did the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer of his loving Dotages ſtop here: for, having warily followed her after ſhe went from the Ball, he ſaw her go into the Houſe of one of the chief Gentlemen of that City, who, among other temporal bleſſings, was happy in a very beautiful Wife. He imagining that this Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade was <hi>Leena,</hi> for ſuch was the fair La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies name of that Houſe, grew more and more in Love, and his Paſſion was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed when he ſaw <hi>Leena</hi> the next day, wear part of thoſe ornaments which he had obſerved on the Maſquerade. Tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore courage from the difficulty of the Enterpriſe, he reſolved to try all means poſſible. Fortune was not averſe in offering them unto him, whilſt that very Evening the ſame Maſquerade came again to the Ball. He, after having wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome time on her, ſeeing no little cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33822:12"/>
in her eyes, the preſs of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple leaving no room for obſervation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted her after this faſhion. Madam, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my tongue were not afraid of committing a raſh offence, it would venture to diſcloſe the paſſion that I nouriſh in my breaſt, and would intercede for a love which is ſo much the greater, by how much the longer it is concealed. If you knew; ſaid ſhe, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that is diſguiſed under this Habit, you would heartily repent your having given ſo much liberty to your tongue. I do not rely, anſwered <hi>Epidorus,</hi> upon outward appearances, but upon the knowledge of your ſingular merit which is matched to an excellent beauty. You, ſays the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querade, ſo you get the name of a lover do not care if you are reputed a Lyar. Tell me, how can you judge of the beauty of my face, which you have not ſeen other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than Maſqued? One may very well, replied <hi>Epidorus,</hi> give judgment upon the brightneſs of the Sun, although it be ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Cloud; and my wicked eyes have forcibly introduc'd the bright image of your beauty into my heart. Lady <hi>Leena,</hi> it is impoſſible to conceal your ſelf from the affection of a Lover who hath the eyes of <hi>Argus.</hi> To ſay that I adore you is the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33822:12"/>
greateſt teſtimony that my mouth can ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, but the leaſt ſentiment that my heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an expreſs. It lyes in you to make me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>appy. Great enterpriſes have great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulties attending them. But Love, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an rob <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf of the power of his Thunder, can alſo make level even Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ains of impoſſibility. He would have gone on, if that the Maſquerade, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome ſhew of anger, had not interrupted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is diſcourſe ſaying, When you ſpoke to me as to a perſon unknown, I did bear with your ignorance; but now ſeeing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou know me, and yet, with a preſumption <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reater than becomes you, dare ſtill to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>empt me, I cannot but blame your inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence. If I did not fear the prejudice ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to my honour from one ſo inferiour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o my Quality, Repentance ſhould be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt puniſhment of your raſhneſs. But whilſt ſhe was ſpeaking theſe words, her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands and her eyes did betray her tongue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd did aſſure <hi>Epidorus,</hi> by all the favours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſible, that thoſe reſentments were the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpulſes of honeſty; and not the effects of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nger. And here the Ball broke up, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon it behoved <hi>Epidorus</hi> to retire accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anied with all thoſe inquietudes which do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſault the youth and imprudence of a lover.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33822:13"/>
He expected the next night, which was the laſt of the <hi>Carnevale,</hi> with thoſe paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deſires which are wont to attend an enamoured Soul. The Stars had ſcarce made any ſhew of the light they had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the Sun, when he went to the uſual Ball. A little after came the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querade, very well known, although ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had us'd a great deal of cunning to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal her ſelf from the curious eye of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus.</hi> He taking her by the hand, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to give credit to his affection with theſe words. Fair <hi>Leena</hi> you may, by your new diſguiſe very well impoſe upon the eyes of others, but not upon my hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which, with its unuſual palpitations and diffuſions of heat to all the parts of my body, doth not only know you, but ador<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you as a Goddeſs. I wiſh, that with your yeſterday Garments, you may have alſo laid aſide that haughtineſs of Spirit that made you ſo averſe to my Love. Know therefore that cruelty is an improper at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute for the divinity of your Beauty and that Beauty which is not communicabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to others is directly oppoſite to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Heaven. If the Heavens ſhould enjoyn me to love you, anſwered the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querade, why then perhaps neither the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33822:13"/>
Laws of honeſty, the hazard of my life, nor the inconſtancy of Men, could bridle my affection. The beauty of your aſpect, added <hi>Epidorus,</hi> is a token ſent you from Heaven, that admoniſheth you not to be too ſparing of your favours, ſince that by enriching your form, it hath impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all other the faireſt ideas imaginable. Let us not fly ſo high as Hyperboles, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Maſquerade. I, as I know my ſelf not to be ſo fair; ſo I would gladly be ſo, that I might better pleaſe him that will love me. But your cunning and my ſimplicity hath made me diſcover the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of my heart to a perſon, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps laughing at my indiſcretion, doth go about to deceive my eaſie nature. It is not juſt that my reputation ſhould venture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch evident dangers. I have ſaid too much. If my face were to be ſeen, the bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es which grief and repentance have cauſed there, would give ſufficient teſtimony of the ſame. The bloud which my heart hath ſent up into my face, is the reproof of my ſoul, that threatens thoſe ſevere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the thoughts only whereof do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright me. In ſaying ſo, ſhe retir'd among other the Maſquerades, leaving <hi>Epidorus</hi> oppreſs'd by a number of thoughts, from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33822:14"/>
which he would not quickly have diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged himſelf, if Love, which commonly is not wanting to help the neceſſities of Lovers, had not ſuccour'd him. Taking therefore his Maſquerade again by the hand, he preſs'd her ſo hard, and promis'd her ſo much, that he obtained leave for a Conference with her the next night, (which was the firſt night in Lent) at a little Window that looked out into a By-ſtreet. With theſe pleaſing hopes he paſs'd away the remainder of that night, expecting the other with many railing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions againſt the Stars, for that they ſtay'd ſo long before they came to celebrate the Funeral of the day. Scarce had the light given place to darkneſs when he was at the appointed window. Although he thought to have anticipated the hour, yet he found himſelf prevented, his beloved having attended his coming, and accuſing him of little love to her ſelf, becauſe he was not there before her. There paſſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Complements between them, and their amorous conceits were without number. They diſcours'd of Conſtancy, Fidelity and Secreſie, as if they never could have had enough of it, inſomuch that the night, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weary of hearing them, ſeemed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33822:14"/>
the day. And the day approaching they departed with promiſe to meet there as often as <hi>Epidorus</hi> ſhould ſee a little white Cloth hanging out at the VVin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. This was done two or three times a Week, and gave ſo great content to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidorus,</hi> that, in compariſon thereof, all other Entertainments were but annoyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces unto him. Yet not believing his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be compleat if he did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it unto others, he yielded ſo much to indiſcretion, as to impart the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of his amours unto many of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidents. He bragg'd that he had won the heart of <hi>Leena,</hi> which had driven the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and affection of a Thouſand Lovers to deſpair. He boaſted to be the poſſeſſor of that beauty which had oblig'd even thoſe men who were addicted to love none but themſelves, unto adoration. Theſe Stories came to the ears of one who being either incredulous or envious, reſolved to watch the proceedings of <hi>Epidorus.</hi> He overheard him one Evening when he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to enter that night into the poſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſion of his Love. And not being able to comply with the felicity of one who was in no point ſuperiour to him, but in the gifts of Fortune; being excited by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33822:15"/>
envy, which always conſpires againſt the ſatisfaction of others, he let looſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of his Rage in a Letter which he ſent unto the Husband of <hi>Leena,</hi> who open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it read what followeth:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Cordelius,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Not to diſcover traiterous actions, is to confeſs ones ſelf an Accomplice in them. I who, by the exceſs of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and the obligations that ly upon me, am deſtinated to the protection of your honour, cannot be ſilent when I ſee it betray'd into the hands of diſhoneſty. The night in which thoſe infamies are acted that obſcure your reputation, hath not darkneſs enough to cover your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. My Zeal implores you to be an eye-witneſs, that you may confeſs <hi>Leena</hi> to be unchaſt, and me your real friend. The ſearching out of the truth hereof I refer to your diſcretion. I am ſorry to diſturb the repoſe of your ſoul with ſo unexpected an advice; but he is to be commended who by diſcovering a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, doth give occaſion for applying the remedies thereunto.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your faithful Friend.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33822:15"/>This Letter rais'd an infinite number of thoughts, and all of them cruel in the mind of <hi>Cordelius.</hi> He thought upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Bloud, Death and Slaughters. Yet the love he bore <hi>Leena</hi> prevailing with him, and prudently weighing what might be the effects of Malice, he reſolved to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing but his own eyes. He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended very urgent affairs to go in all haſte into the Country, and departed not without the Tears of <hi>Leena,</hi> who lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every moment of his abſence. <hi>Cordeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> kept himſelf hid all the reſt of that day, and at night went to ſpy out the betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his Honour. In the mean time <hi>Leena</hi> being fallen into a moſt ſweet ſleep, was awaked, not without diſturbance, by the calling of her Nurſe. She inform'd her that <hi>Cordelius</hi> was juſt then upon entring into the embraces of <hi>Cinicia</hi> her Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, and that ſhe had told her of it, that ſhe might be no hindrance to it. <hi>Leena</hi> was apt enough to believe this, knowing the Genius of her Husband and the little honeſty of her Maid. So much the rather, for that ſhe had not been without ſome jealouſie before, and had made ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of it. She quickly put on her Cloathes, and not being willing that the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33822:16"/>
Nurſe ſhould follow her, that ſo ſhe might the more freely reprehend the incontinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Gordelius,</hi> ſhe went towards her Maids Chamber. There ſhe found her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who, with his Sword ready drawn in his hand, was running upon her for to kill her. He did not do it, either to let her firſt ſee the death of her Paramour; or elſe becauſe the Mercy of Heaven would not permit that her ſuſpected innocence ſhould have undeſerved puniſhment. <hi>Leena,</hi> although ſhe were full of anger, yet thought it more ſafe to uſe entreaties than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs. Throwing her ſelf at his feet, and intermixing her words with tears, ſhe ſaid, Sir, if the honeſt embraces of a Servant do pleaſe you better than thoſe of a VVife, I know not how to oppoſe your ſatisfaction. I proffer my ſelf to be the Procureſs of your pleaſures, if you will do me the honour to command me. But that in the loſs of my honour I ſhould ſee alſo the danger of my life, I cannot but lament the rigours of my Deſtiny that hath made me ſo unhappy. Is therefore the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent diſhoneſty of a Serving-Maid more powerful with you than the chaſt delights of a VVife, whoſe deſires are wholly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to your beck? O that <hi>Cordelius</hi> ſhould
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33822:16"/>
ſo much forget himſelf, and that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſhould alter their influence for to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment me! Here <hi>Cordelius</hi> interrupted her, ſaying, Falſe VVoman, thy lies and tears would have perſuaded me ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if my eyes had not been witneſſes of thy diſhoneſty. Prepare thy ſelf to die, for it is not reaſon that ſhe ſhould live, who hath murdered my Reputation. But firſt tell me where you hide that Raſcal that has had the impudence to violate my Bed. <hi>Leena</hi> not being able to endure theſe terms which toucht her to the very quick, replied, For to excuſe your amorous thefts by ſpecious pretences, you go about to accuſe my Chaſtity. This is not conſonant to your prudence and my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. I am yours, and only yours, Malice it ſelf cannot find that I have prejudiced your honour, ſo much as in thought, much leſs in deed. I do appeal to your ſelf, at ſuch time as the inordinate deſire of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying a Servant-maid, or the diſpleaſure of being intercepted ſhall not have poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ſoul. <hi>Cordelius,</hi> being more high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incenſed hereat, with great fury ask'd her, what ſervant? or what amours ſhe ſpoke of? VVhereto <hi>Leena</hi> repeating to him all that the Nurſe had told her, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33822:17"/>
he alſo hearing it confirm'd by her own mouth, ran preſently to the Maids Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and there found her lovingly in Bed with <hi>Epidorus.</hi> He was ready to have made him a ſacrifice to his fury, had not he been diverted by the perſuaſions of his VVife. He was contented at laſt that <hi>Epidorus</hi> ſhould Marry <hi>Cinicia,</hi> who came to be a ſervant more through the injuries of Fortune, than by the qualities of her Deſcent. Hereunto <hi>Epidorus</hi> readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, without reply, the fear of Death making him honeſt whether he would or no. After this <hi>Cordelius</hi> embraced <hi>Leena,</hi> and excuſed what he had done in ſenſe of Honour, for that he had heard <hi>Epidorus</hi> make a Call with a little whiſtle, and then ſaw him brought into the Houſe. Prudent <hi>Leena</hi> was well ſatisfied with theſe juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, rejoycing that ſhe had eſcaped a danger which was ſo much the greater in that it was not foreſeen, and which, at one and the ſame time, did threaten both her Life and Reputation.</p>
               <p>This may ſerve to advertiſe Husbands not to run headlong into the ſuſpicion of their VVives diſhoneſty; may teach VVives not to give too much liberty to their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens; and laſtly, may be an example to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33822:17"/>
all thoſe that go about to debauch the VVives of other Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="novel">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lovanius</hi> coming to a certain Houſe that was accidentally ſet on fire, is inflamed with the love of <hi>Deadora,</hi> who, proving not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, correſponds with him, and, to give her ſelf the better opportunity, ſhe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly condeſcends that her Husband, while ſhe enjoyeth her lover, ſhould embrace <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> her Chamber-maid; ſhe falling in love with <hi>Lovanius,</hi> betrayeth her Miſtreſs, who tranſported by jealous fury, openeth the way to her own and others deſtruction.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVEL</hi> III.</head>
               <p>THere lived as a Student, in the famous Academy of <hi>Bologna, Lovanius</hi> Son to the Count of <hi>Roccabruna,</hi> a young Man who by his bodily perfection and affable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour, did tyrannize over the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all thoſe that had the fortune to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33822:18"/>
know him. He went one day a walking towards the Walls of the City, when he was ſtopt in the way by ſome voices, who crying out Fire, Fire, did pitifully call for aſſiſtance. Among other Women that, being deſperately affrighted at this acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, did exceedingly weep and wail, there was a Gentlewoman, who though the Roſes in her Complexion were turn'd into Lillies, yet was there left an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a Garden full of Beauty. This Lady nevertheleſs, having a courage great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the danger, was not at all daunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though her being forſaken of all, and unable to remedy it her ſelf, made her a little fearful. <hi>Lovanius</hi> ſeeing no body move, the Neighbours being fled from their Houſes, and there being none but a company of poor Women, who, by their loud ſhreeking, did augment the terror and confuſion, he reſolv'd to go himſelf with his ſervants, and help to extinguiſh that fire which, having already gotten head, began with towring flames to ſoar aloft. Going therefore into the Palace where the fire was very furious, after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpoke to <hi>Deadora</hi> (for this was the Miſtreſs of the Houſe her name) that ſhe ſhould be of good chear, and put away
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33822:18"/>
all her fears, he went, with his ſervants and ſome others that came to help, to the top of the Houſe. There he wrought ſo much with his hands, and commands, that the Fire in a little while, was loſt in a cloud of Smoak. He was ſcarce come down from the Roof of the Houſe when he was met by <hi>Gelaſius</hi> the Husband of that Lady who, hearing of the danger, came running home. Here paſſed many words between them, and all of them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courteous, <hi>Gelaſius</hi> was not wanting to offer unto him the Patronage of that houſe which he had made his own by preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it from being burnt. There came alſo <hi>Deadora</hi> to give him thanks in ſuch obliging manner, that <hi>Lovanius</hi> felt thoſe flames kindled in his heart which he had a little before extinguiſhed. He had look'd upon her before with ſentiments of pity whilſt ſhe, being oppreſſed by fear, could do nothing but weep and wail; the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning colour of her face having not had force enough to ſet his ſoul on fire: but now that her Courage had reſtor'd her wonted beauty, and that the brightneſs of her eyes was not clouded with tears, his pity was changed into love. Thus <hi>Lovanius</hi> dedicated his affection wholly to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33822:19"/>
this Beauty; which <hi>Deadora</hi> ſoon perceiv'd, and ſo much the ſooner, becauſe in his tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leave, he inſpir'd his very ſoul into her with a ſigh. Nevertheleſs ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not to ſee it, either for to give greater credit unto her honeſty, or for that ſhe would not ſo ſoon entruſt her ſelf to the fidelity of any man. And although <hi>Lovanius</hi> continually waited on her both to Church and at Balls, yet he reap'd no other fruits of his labour than ſalutes and indifferent looks, which might rather be imputed unto common civility, than affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate courteſie. The young Gentleman, not being able to reſiſt the violent torments of his ſoul, he gave vent to his paſſion by writing theſe words:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The flames that burnt your Houſe were deſtinated to torment my ſoul. I would have hid them, but that fire ſuppreſſed doth break forth with greater violence, and makes all ſuccours come too late. I would have quenched them, but that they being ſupernatural, my tears could do no more than make my grief the more ſenſible. I do therefore, Fair Lady, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore that pity for extinguiſhing my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33822:19"/>
which I did heartily contribute without ſo much as expecting any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty from you. You have reaſon to have compaſſion of me, becauſe you have experienced the damage and dangers that do accompany fires. I hope that a Lady of your fair quality will not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate your fame with foul ingratitude. Help me, I pray you, if for nothing elſe, for that you may not loſe a ſervant who loves you as much as is poſſible for him, though not ſo much as you deſerve. The hopes of my life depend upon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your anſwer; I eſteeming your favours to be the true aliment of my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Having folded up and ſealed this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he beſought Fortune to give it a ſafe delivery. He thought in himſelf that the moſt reſolute means were alſo the moſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous. To make uſe of Women for this purpoſe, were to ſtain the reputation of the Lady, and to provoke her to anger, while he ſhould gain her love. At length reſolving, by a raſh action, to overcome all the impediments that oppoſed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, upon a certain day that <hi>Deadora</hi> was ſitting in the Church at Prayers, he neatly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33822:20"/>
rolled up the Letter, and threw it into her boſom, ſo cleverly that no body perceived it. <hi>Deadora</hi> being ſurprized hereat, and ſeeing that to make a noiſe would but bring her into diſgrace, ſhe cunningly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd the Letter, and return'd very much troubled in mind unto her Houſe. As ſoon as ſhe was alone her curioſity, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps her love too, induced her to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Paper. She had not read it over, before ſhe gave her ſelf up for vanquiſhed. Thoſe expreſſions were too powerful for the weakneſs of a Womans heart (which is apt to receive any impreſſion) to reſiſt. Her amorous deſires thus tyrannizing over her, ſhe found no other repoſe than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude. She ſummon'd all the faculties of her Soul to come to counſel with her, which after a debate did finally Vote for <hi>Lovanius.</hi> Whereupon, being compelled by that force which knoweth nothing of reaſon, and which works with greateſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence where it finds moſt reſiſtance, ſhe return'd him this anſwer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Lovanius,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>If I did not think I ſhould incur your diſdain with declaring my ſelf ſo eaſily overcome, I would frankly ſay that I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33822:20"/>
love you, and that I am yours. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know the inconſtancy of Mens minds to be ſuch, as to ſet little value up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what is gotten and enjoyed without much labour, I therefore beſeech you to abandon that enterprize which cannot take effect without endangering both my Life and Reputation. Yet I have a ſoul ſo full of gratitude that I cannot but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to give them ſatisfaction, who have ſo obligingly afforded me their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour in time of need. I therefore reſt aſſured that ſo worthy a Gentleman who is endowed with all the graces of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and of Fortune, will not diſturb the repoſe of my faithful heart, nor torment the inclinations of a Woman that, in ſpight of her heart, confeſſes her ſelf to be yours. You did ſo courteouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern your ſelf in quenching the late fire which exercis'd its fury only on things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible; that it is not juſt you ſhould now foment it in my ſoul, with danger of conſuming both my Life and Honour. If I could have ſhook off that Yoke which is ſo much the heavier for that it came rather by Deſtiny than by my good will, you ſhould not have been before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with me in Writing. Pardon me if I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33822:21"/>
undecently trample on the Laws of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, and the honeſty becoming our Sex; ſince that Reaſon is the firſt thing whereof Love depriveth us. But I fear I have diſcovered my mind too much to one that perhaps will laugh at my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter, coming privately to the hands of <hi>Lovanius,</hi> fill'd him with ſo great joy that he was not able to contain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. He knew very well that thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>Deadora</hi> were not feigned, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thoſe repulſes were indeed invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and the doubts therein mentioned were no other than aſſurances of love. Hence he inferred that the affection of that Lady was greater than he could have imagined, and therefore, without ſending any more Letters, he brought his buſineſs about ſo well, that he got the opportunity of ſpeaking to her at a little Window, where they agreed upon the end of their amorous pretenſions. <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of <hi>Deadora,</hi> was ſo addicted to all Women that, like a Cameleon that puts on all colours that come near him, he changed his love and deſires with all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. For to ſatisfie his greedy Luſts
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33822:21"/>
he made no diſtinction between Nobility and Beauty. He confeſs'd himſelf to be as ſoon caught by Silver Hairs as by Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Locks. A Lady of Honour, and the moſt arrant Strumpet had a like power over him. That Beauty wherein the moſt critical malice could find no fault, had no greater triumph over his affection, than a face transformed by a thouſand blemiſhes and imperfections. <hi>Deadora</hi> being acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Genius of her Husband, thought of this means to enjoy her lover. She knew that <hi>Aleria</hi> her Chambermaid had been ſollicited by promiſes, gifts, and many times with threatnings to comply with him in his Amorous Debauches. <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> being aſſaulted with many unchaſt thoughts, would eaſily have conſented, had not ſhe been with-held by the fear of her Miſtreſs who, with <hi>Argus</hi>'s Eyes, did watch over the diſſolute affections of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſius. Deadora</hi> therefore, willing to have the opportunity of being with her Lover, was content that <hi>Aleria</hi> in the mean while ſhould entertain her Husband. Which ſucceeded happily oftentimes, the hot Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Year alſo concurring in favour of their loves. <hi>Gelaſius</hi> and <hi>Deadora</hi> lay in two Chambers apart, ſo that <hi>Lovanius</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:33822:22"/>
being brought into a Ground-room, whilſt that <hi>Gelaſius</hi> enjoyed <hi>Aleria,</hi> he kept company with <hi>Deadora;</hi> and <hi>Aleria</hi> in one and the ſame time did ſerve to guard her Miſtreſs, pleaſe her Maſter, and ſolace her ſelf. But becauſe amorous felicity is an <hi>Ephemera</hi> that is born and dies in one day, Fortune was reſolv'd to precipitate them with as much eaſe as ſhe had before exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. <hi>Lovanius</hi> was brought into the houſe, by <hi>Aleria,</hi> one evening a little ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than ordinary. She, having received him with a thouſand Careſſes, expreſſing the ardor that ſhe nouriſhed in her breaſt, told him that <hi>Deadora,</hi> having not quite ſupped, could not come yet awhile, but that, in the mean time, ſhe had commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to entertain him. <hi>Lovanius</hi> thanked her very kindly, telling her, this was not the firſt obligation ſhe had laid upon him. <hi>Aleria</hi> had not patience to hear him any more, but, taking him by the hand, ſaid, Mr. <hi>Lovanius,</hi> there is no greater unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs than to ſee another gather the fruit of ones own labour. I have done very much for to promote your love, and have gained nothing but fears and dangers. Is it poſſible, in gratitude at leaſt, if not for love, that I may not merit the favour of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33822:22"/>
your kindneſs? Certainly I do not envy the happineſs of my Miſtreſs in poſſeſſing your whole Heart; I only bewail the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of my Fortune which hath put me in a condition to be deſpiſed, even by thoſe for whom I continually do ſervices. Having thus ſpoken ſhe kiſſed his Hand, which ſhe held preſſed between her own, with ſo much paſſion, that <hi>Lovanius,</hi> who at firſt laughed at her folly, being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſiſt any longer, let himſelf be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by ſenſuality; ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the Features of <hi>Aleria</hi> were ſo excellent, that he rather would have been counted a fool, than a conſtant lover who ſhould have let ſlip the occaſion of enjoying her. <hi>Lovanius</hi> and <hi>Aleria</hi> were ingulfed in Amorous Pleaſures, when <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora,</hi> thinking long e're ſhe was called, and perhaps not being without jealouſie (ſince true Lovers pay this intereſt for their pleaſure) having ſeen her Husband in bed, ſhe came ſoftly down into the ground Chamber. There having found her lover engaged in amorous action, being hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by a precipitous rage, without remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the dangers that were imminent to her Life and Honour, ſhe began furiouſly to lay about her both with her hands and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33822:23"/>
tongue. Traitors, ſaid ſhe, do you thus triumph over my diſgrace? are theſe the rewards of my confidence and fidelity? I'll handle you in ſuch manner, that by ſeeing you buried in my deſtruction, I will rejoice that my ruine ſhall not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted either by your deriſion or laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Theſe words were accompanied with ſo many blows and bites, that fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bloud in many places about <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. Lovanius,</hi> in this interim, throwing himſelf at her feet, entreated her with ſuch ſweet words as would have ſoftned the hardeſt ſtones. Sometimes he put her in mind of the danger their lives were in. Sometimes he excuſed his own errour, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing amendment. And other times he proteſted that his body had ſinned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of his ſoul. <hi>Deadora</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, being deaf to theſe ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and humiliations, continued her aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults both in words and deeds; when <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> with a look full of horrour and fierceneſs, came thither. He had waking long attended <hi>Aleria's</hi> coming, whereupon riſing for to look after her, he came where he heard, though not diſtinctly, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of <hi>Deadora,</hi> the crys of <hi>Aleria,</hi> and the prayers of <hi>Lovanius. Gelaſius</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33822:23"/>
taking a Poniard in his Hand, ran in a rage whither the noiſe called him. He had no ſooner ſeen <hi>Lovanius</hi> embracing his Wifes knees, but he concluded him to be the enemy of her Chaſtity, and the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his Houſe; wherefore, running furiouſly on him, he wounded him in ſuch manner in the head, that not being able to ſupport himſelf, he fell flat upon the ground, with the Agony of Death upon him, which alſo appeared more terrible unto him, becauſe he ſaw that his ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities had prepared a grave, not only for himſelf, but alſo for <hi>Deadora. Gelaſius</hi> ſeeing <hi>Lovanius</hi> in a condition not to live long, much leſs to make any defence, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to his Wife, with a tone ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible that would have ſtruck horrour into the ſtouteſt heart, he ſaid, Woman, thy offence is ſo heinous, that to let it go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed would be an effect rather of weakneſs than of compaſſion. Yet, the characters of my former affection being ſtill imprinted in my mind, I will pardon thee, but on this condition, that ſeeing this Adulterer hath gotten thy heart, thou wilt, by the help of this weapon, tear it from his breaſt. <hi>Deadora</hi> taking the Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, with an undaunted courage, greater
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33822:24"/>
than is required in any Woman, ſaid unto him, Sir, the errors of love do deſerve ſome kind of pardon, becauſe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed rather from Fate, than out of choice. But I confeſs my ſelf unworthy of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I could not regulate my diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. She ſpoke theſe words, and then, making as if ſhe would have run the Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger into <hi>Lovanius</hi>'s body, ſhe ſtabb'd her Husband to the heart, who ſcarce could ſay, Curſed Woman, doſt thou thus, in one moment rob me of my Honour and my Life? but loſing his Speech in a number of groans, in a manner threatning rather than yielding to death, he unhappily departed this life. <hi>Deadora,</hi> having performed this much more generous than juſt enterprize, ſhe ran to ſuck in the laſt breath of <hi>Lova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> who, ſtriving againſt the pangs of Death, ſpoke thus unto her. My dear <hi>Deadora,</hi> I now dye contented, in that I dye not unrevenged. Pardon me, I pray you, and let the chaſtiſement of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane errour terminate with him that hath committed it. For Gods ſake let not your anger diſturb my aſhes. But Oh me! this is the laſt minute of my life. Give me, O my Dear, your laſt kiſſes for a conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at this my departure. In ending theſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33822:24"/>
words he ended his days. <hi>Deadora,</hi> being oppreſſed with grief, ſtood immoveable as a Statue; and, after a Deluge of tears, ſhe cryed out ſaying, Stay a little O thou Soul of my moſt dear <hi>Lovanius.</hi> 'Tis not juſt that thou ſhouldſt go alone into the Shades. In ſaying ſo, ſhe gave her ſelf a Stab upon the Heart, and thereupon, in a moment, ſhe pow'red forth her Soul with her Bloud. <hi>Aleria,</hi> who in the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of theſe Tragedies had ſuffer'd the torments of a thouſand Deaths, flying from the ſight and interrogation of all thoſe whom the noiſe had drawn thither in great numbers, and hating at once both to ſee her ſelf and the light, retired unto the uppermoſt part of the Houſe. Thereby fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Cord, and therewith miſerably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring, ſhe gave a worthy reward to her own immodeſty.</p>
               <p>From hence it may be gathered, that the joys of all illegitimate love do termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in ſorrows, and that unchaſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can have no other than an unhappy end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="novel">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:33822:25"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>The Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelnovo,</hi> in a certain great exigency, ſends for aſſiſtance to the Marqueſs <hi>Oliverio.</hi> He being fervently enamoured of her, doth moſt readily comply with her deſires. The Counteſs having her want ſupplied, doth, by a neat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance, carried on by favour of the night, both ſave her own honour, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the diſcretion of the Marqueſs.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVELL</hi> IV.</head>
               <p>IN the City of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> ſituate in the Province of <hi>Puglia,</hi> upon the Confines of <hi>Monferrat,</hi> there was a moſt Noble Gentlewoman whom I will at preſent diſtinguiſh by no other name than that of the Counteſs. This Lady was graced with ſuch ſingular perfection of Beauty, that ſhe could not be beheld by Men without ardent love, nor by Women without great envy. The content which Lovers had in looking upon the moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33822:25"/>
features of her Face, did extort from them the loſs of their liberty. In ſhort, this glorious Sun did dazle the hearts no leſs than the eyes of the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. He was rather deem'd a fool than wiſe, who could not be ſubject to ſuch ſweet Tyranny, and he was almoſt reput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Sacrilegious Perſon who did not offer up his heart in Sacrifice to this idolized Beauty. This Treaſury of all the riches of Nature was, by right of Matrimony, in the poſſeſſion of the Count <hi>de Caſtelnovo,</hi> a Gentleman endued with all thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours that either Fortune can diſpence, or Vertue can obtain: but, as it was thought, little loved by the Counteſs, becauſe he, for the moſt part, either ſojourning at the Courts of Princes, or exerciſing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in Armies, was more converſant in Martial Affairs than thoſe of <hi>Venus.</hi> This belief got ſo much ground in the hearts of many, as to give them hopes of ſubduing that Fortreſs which was guarded only by beauty that might eaſily be ſuborned with gifts, or vanquiſhed by the power of ſervices and addreſſes. But they ſaw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves greatly miſtaken, for they found ſuch reſiſtance in the Vertue and Chaſtity of this Lady, that ſome of them were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33822:26"/>
wholly to abandon the Enterprize, others to raiſe the Siege, and otherſome to expect thoſe opportunities which are the genuine products of time. Only the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Oliverio,</hi> who was the moſt noble and richeſt among them, was not a jot moved on the retreat of the reſt. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted his aſſaults with ſo much the more Vigour, by how much the leſs hopes he had of Victory. The many denials, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes and diſdains he met with, were but ſo many winds that did rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame than extinguiſh the fire in his heart. And though he could not hope to make any further progreſs in the conqueſt of this Ladies Chaſtity, yet he made uſe of all thoſe means that might make him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the character of a true lover, ſince he could not attain to that of being belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And ſo much the rather, for that having, by his liberality gotten the good will of all thoſe that ſerved her, the poor Gentlewoman had her ears continually filled with the praiſes of this Gentleman, ſince that all the Family were never wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in ſetting forth ſometimes his Valour, othertimes his Birth, now his Goodneſs, then his Riches, one while his handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and other whiles the magnanimity
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33822:26"/>
of ſo great a Perſon. And although theſe ſo often repeated commendations did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline her to admire ſuch rare qualities, yet they did not oblige her to any other love than what Vertue is wont to produce in a Noble Breaſt. But that which <hi>Oliverio,</hi> with all his Love-traps, could not do in a very long time, Fortune (as the poor Gentleman believed) did bring to paſs in a moment. The Counteſs had a Brother a Young Man and rich, and let that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to denote him inſolent. There was no Riot in the City wherein he was not either intereſſed or principal. The Night, which brings quiet and repoſe, even up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inſatiable cruelty of Wild Beaſts, did make him reſtleſs, whilſt that, being accompanied by many like himſelf, he rambled up and down the City equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing his affronts to all; thoſe only being exempt from his inſolences who had the good luck not to meet him. But, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment oftentimes attending wicked actions, while he would, one night, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly enter the Houſe of an Honourable Lady, and was already breaking open the Windows and Doors, he, with four of his Companions, were taken by the Watch, having neither time, nor courage to make
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33822:27"/>
reſiſtance, ſince the ill Language where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they had menaced this Lady had raiſed almoſt all the Neighborhood. As ſoon as his being made a Priſoner was publickly known, complaints came in ſo faſt againſt him, that he was in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of loſing his Life. The Counteſs, who loved him dearly, and could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to ſee him ſubjected to open cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, having no ready money, pawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the greater part of her Jewels to Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants for a Thouſand Duckets. With this Money ſhe prevail'd ſo much upon the Governour, that he, being dazled with the Splendor of her Gold, could not ſee Juſtice. So that the young man with his Companions made their eſcape by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of this Governour who, being afraid that his Avarice might be diſcovered, was willing that the Priſoner by flying ſhould take off the ſtrength of the evidence which would have prov'd the Judge alſo to be guilty. The Counteſs had not long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the liberty of her Brother, but that a Letter came from her Husband which drave her to the vey brink of Deſperation. The Count commanded that, without the leaſt delay ſhe ſhould come to him to <hi>Millan,</hi> in her richeſt attire, for to wait
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33822:27"/>
upon the Empreſs, who was expected eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day to paſs that way. The poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being oppreſſed by a multitude of thoughts, knew not what reſolution to take that might not be either diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or dangerous. To go to <hi>Millan</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe Ornaments which are befitting ſuch occaſions, would bring much preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice upon the reputation of her Grandeur. And to diſcover to her Husband the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſing of her Brother, ſhe could not do it without incurring his diſpleaſure, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that many important differences had hapned between them. After many thoughts that came in her Head, ſhe was forced to yield to neceſſity, and taking Pen, Ink and Paper, ſhe writ as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>
                              <hi>My Lord</hi> Oliverio,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>If I ſhould ſay I do not love you I ſhould certainly lye, ſince the confidence I have in you I cannot but acknowledge it to be the lawful iſſue of love. I love you <hi>Oliverio,</hi> and therefore, although it be a blemiſh to my Honour, I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to your favour. I have great oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for a thouſand Duckets for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem my Jewels, becauſe I muſt be at
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33822:28"/>
                           <hi>Milan</hi> at the arrival there of the Empreſs. If you can lend 'em me until my return, it will oblige my heart to a perpetual cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with you. But Gentlemen of your worth do act by Principles of Generoſity; and then what can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from a heart tyed up to the good opinion of the World, and the Fidelity due to Matrimony? Yet I promiſe my ſelf that the greatneſs of your mind will not diſdain the ſervice of</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt devoted <hi>Counteſs.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Having Sealed the Letter, ſhe gave it to a Lacquey, telling him it came from her Husband, and that he ſhould carry it to the Marqueſs, ſhe being unwilling to truſt to the ſilence or infidelity of any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. <hi>Oliverio</hi> had ſcarce run over the Letter, but he thought himſelf to be in a Dream. He could hardly give credit to his happineſs which was ſo much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by how much the more it was unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. He had ſo great conſolation within himſelf, that he let drop ſome tears for joy. The firſt ſurprize, which putteth a Man beſide himſelf, being over, he retunred an anſwer in theſe following terms:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:33822:28"/>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I wiſh I had a thouſand Souls, as well as I have a Thouſand Duckets, for to ſacrifice them all unto your Service. I am really to thank you for the honour you do me in asking ſo obligingly what you might have commanded as your own. But I am ſo much confounded with joy and obligation, that I cannot better expreſs my ſelf than by ſilence. Yet I rejoice within my ſelf for that you have been pleas'd to ſoder my ſincerity with Gold, and ſo much the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that your asking of outward Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es makes me believe you will accept the inward treaſures of my heart. I hope that theſe double Duckets will not argue me to be double-minded, and I ſhall eſteem it my greateſt honour to be own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obliged Servant The Marqueſs <hi>Oliverio.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>He ſent, without any delay, both the Letter and the Ducats to the Counteſs, who, redeeming her Jewels, went imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to <hi>Milan,</hi> where ſhe came in the very nick of time for to meet the Empreſs.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33822:29"/>
Here ſhe made ſo fair a ſhow, that the Empreſs declared her ſelf much honoured by thoſe who ſent ſo beautiful a perſon to meet her. The envy of the Ladies was converted into wonder; and it ſeemed as if Nature had robbed all other Women of their perfections, for to beſtow them wholly upon her. Th' Empreſs, having preſented her with a very fair Necklace, departed from <hi>Milan;</hi> and ſhe preſently returned to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where <hi>Oliverio</hi> did attend her coming with thoſe impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiences that, like Furies, do continually torment the ſouls of Lovers. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs would not be ſeen at this Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <hi>Milan,</hi> either becauſe he would not give occaſion of ſuſpicion to ſo many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving eyes; or elſe that he might avoid the obligation of waiting upon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. The Counteſs was no ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned but he ſent to congratulate her arrival, and to recommend himſelf unto her favour. She gave him to underſtand, the ſame evening, that a little after mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night he muſt come to a Window that looked out into a little by-Street. <hi>Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> went accordingly, and at the hour appointed, heard himſelf called by the Counteſs. I cannot expreſs the paſſion
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33822:29"/>
of <hi>Oliverio</hi> upon this firſt encounter, he felt the extremities both of heat and cold at one and the ſame time. He did in ſuch manner confound her praiſes with his thanks, that he could ſcarce make himſelf intelligible. The Counteſs anſwered all he ſaid in words ſo affectionate and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that, at the ſame time, ſhe let him know both her affection and diſcretion. The Conference ended in this concluſion, that the next night he ſhould come in at the Garden-gate, but with expreſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion that he ſhould have no light. To which the Marqueſs obligingly anſwered, that there needed no light where the Sun ſhin'd. He being departed, ſpent the reſt of that night in a thouſand love-frenzies. He no ſooner ſaw the Sun riſe, but he wiſht it ſet, and did exclaim oftentimes againſt the ſlowneſs of its courſe, becauſe it did not run ſo faſt as he deſired. He alſo blamed the Night which, ſtriving for Empire with the Day, did ſtay ſo long from exerciſing its Dominion in the Air. At length the wiſhed for hour came, whereupon he went haſtily unto the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and finding the Door only ſhut to, he went directly to the Counteſſes Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. She, who expected him, taking
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33822:30"/>
him by the hand and ſaid, My friend, you muſt of neceſſity, ſacrifice this night unto ſilence, if ſo be that you have any reſpect either for my Reputation or my Life. My Women do lye ſo near my Chamber that the leaſt whiſper would be overheard by them. And then my love is not ſo baſe as to be entruſted to any ſervile ſoul; and the rather, becauſe great Enjoyments do not admit of ſpeaking. She gave him no time to make any anſwer, but brought him into the Chamber, and there told him in his ear that he ſhould undreſs and go to Bed, while ſhe would go and ſee if her Maids were aſleep. <hi>Oliverio</hi> was ſcarce lain down when there came into his Arms a Beauty, by ſo much the more perfect, by how much the leſs ſubject it was to the eyes. What they here did my Pen dares not publiſh, leſt I ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane the Secrets of Love. Let it ſuffice to ſay that he, being raviſhed with the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe embraces, did bleſs the time wherein he had endured ſo many labours, ſorrows and torments, ſeeing all paſſed troubles did ſerve for no other end than to aggrandize his preſent content. But, leſt the Light ſhould diſcover their amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Theft, <hi>Oliverio</hi> went away before day,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33822:30"/>
and being enjoyned not to uſe any words, he took his leave with a multitude of kiſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. And then, retiring unto his own Houſe, he did, by ſleep and repoſe, recruit himſelf of his late labours, which yet were ſo pleaſing unto him, that he thought of nothing more than of repeating them. About Noon he roſe up when one of his Servants brought him a Thouſand Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats with a Letter, which he having o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, in great diſpleaſure, read what follows:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>
                              <hi>My Lord</hi> Oliverio,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I return you the Money you ſo obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly lent me, having made uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as long as my occaſions required. I do not do this for to take off the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I have to your affection, but that I may not be wanting in what is my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And you may aſſure your ſelf, that your courteſie ſhall never be forgotten ſo long as I breath. Let this be eſteemed by you as an honour that you have brought under ſubjection a ſoul that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew how to ſubmit to any one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and be pleas'd to accept for</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your very affectionate and moſt obliged Servant The <hi>Counteſs.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33822:31"/>This Letter did ſo perplex the mind of the Marqueſs that he, believing it to be a cheat, did read it over and over many times. He knew not what to imagine, ſince that the ſweet kiſſes, and the moſt endearing embraces of the preceeding night ought not to have begotten ſuch ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and cold expreſſions. After a great confuſion of troubled thoughts, he wrote thus in anſwer:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Fair Lady,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>They have reaſon that ſay, Money takes away a mans repoſe, your Ducats have put me into a mortal inquietude. You ought not, Madam, to have ſent me that which is your own, ſuppoſing that it had been mine. And if my demerits or hard Fortune would have it ſo; why did you not alſo ſend me back my heart, which I have conſecrated to your Beauties? It is a cruel ſort of Liberality for you to ſend me Gold, which is but a vile excrement of the Earth; and to keep back my ſoul which is the very eſſence of a Man. That I may the better expreſs my grief, pleaſe to take the trouble of coming to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33822:31"/>
the little Window at the ſame hour as before. In the mean time pray forget not</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obliged Servant <hi>Oliverio.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſent the Letter, and with great impatience expected the night, he went to the place appointed, where he found the Counteſs. After Salutation the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs fell upon expoſtulation for her hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent the Money, which he did with ſo lively a reſentment, that if he ſhed no tears it was the effect of his grief which did not admit of evaporation both by the mouth, and by the eyes. And why, anſwer'd the Counteſs with a gentle ſmile, would you not have me reſtore to you your own? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, reply'd <hi>Oliverio,</hi> ſince I have receiv'd the honour of your favour, I have nothing that is not abſolutely yours. Pray do not ſo much embitter our paſſed ſweetneſſes. And what ſweetneſſes were theſe, I pray, ſaid the Counteſs? Is it poſſible, anſwer'd <hi>Oliverio,</hi> that the interpoſition of one only day ſhould ſo much eclipſe your memory, as to forget thoſe ſweet endearments that were both given and received? Is it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33822:32"/>
poſſible that thoſe ſprightly kiſſes, which every moment brought our very Souls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the confines of our lips, ſhould have inſtill'd the Water of <hi>Lethe</hi> into your heart? I ſhall rather put my ſelf into Oblivion, than forget the pleaſure I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by ſuch ſweet remembrances. The Counteſs interrupted him, ſaying, My Lord Marqueſs, I will undeceive you, it not being juſt that your Opinion ſhould arraign my Honeſty, which hitherto hath had no other ſtains than thoſe which it may have receiv'd from your deſire and belief. For to pleaſe you I put a trick upon you, thereby to anſwer, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, both my own obligation and your affection. Your amorous actions of the laſt night were with my Chambermaid <hi>Aleria,</hi> my Birth, and the Honour of my Husband, not permitting me more. She is here at hand for to teſtifie unto you the truth hereof. <hi>Oliverio</hi> did not ſtay to hear any further but, being deviliſh mad went home to his houſe, deviſing a thouſand ways how to bring the Fame and Life of the Counteſs to deſtruction. Yet, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting afterward with reaſon, he admir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the prudence of that Lady who, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any prejudice to her Honour, could
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33822:32"/>
faſten ſo fine a Jeſt upon her Lover, and changed his Senſuality into Friendſhip and Reſpect.</p>
               <p>Here Ladies of Honour may be inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how to defend themſelves in ſuch hard caſes without hazarding their Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and Gentlemen may be warned not to attempt the Chaſtity of a prudent Lady, ſince they get nothing thereby but frauds and repulſes. It not being blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to make uſe ſometimes of eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for to eſcape the tyranny of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="novel">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:33822:33"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>The Count of <hi>Villa Franca,</hi> being deceived by finding of a Letter doth believe his Wife to be an Adultereſs. And, whilſt he goes about to take her in the fact, he finds out new matter of ſuſpicion. He was near taking a very ſevere revenge upon her, when he is informed of her innocency, and given to underſtand that the errour did ariſe from a certain likeneſs of Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVEL</hi> V.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman (who for that he is of High Birth, we will call him by the borrowed name of the Count <hi>de Villa Franca</hi>) for to avoid the heat of Summer, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, with his Wife, near to the <hi>Euganean</hi> Hills, to enjoy the Air of a little Mount whereupon, in ſpight of the Dog-days, there was a continual Spring. Here he paſſed away his time by ſpreading Nets for Birds, and ſetting traps for Beaſts. He
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33822:33"/>
robbed his Body of reſt, and his eyes of ſleep, for to ſacrifice them to the hopes he had of prey. He always got up before Sun-riſing, and it ſeemed that this New <hi>Titon</hi> did nothing more than make love to <hi>Aurora.</hi> One morning among the reſt, while he was in ſearch of ſome young Nightingals before they were well fledg'd, he followed his Game to the very out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Confines of his Vineyard which, being very great, had no fence either of Walls or Hedges. And looking narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after thoſe little Birds-neſts who, by cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the old one, did unwittingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray themſelves, he caſt his eye upon a Letter that lay among a company of leaves, and did ſeem as if it were afraid of being diſcovered. He, taking it up and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerving the Seal, was on a ſudden agitated with divers thoughts. Scarce had he opened it but that, ſeeing the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and Subſcription to be his Wifes, he grew Horn-mad. After a little pauſe, which was accompanied by thoſe tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary paſſions that do aſſault a Soul that is govern'd both by honour and by love; he curſorily read over the Letter, which contain'd theſe expreſſions:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:33822:34"/>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Friend,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>She that loves cannot do all that ſhe would. Fortune would not be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Goddeſs, if ſhe did not many times drive the patient ſufferings of a lover into deſperations. Pardon therefore that impotency, which hitherto hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental, and not voluntary. She that is in love is always more unhappy than all others, becauſe ſhe coveteth more than others. This night only Fate grants me the favour of a conſolation to my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiences. They that have authority to watch over the motions of my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be either abſent or conſenting. I, in an Habit different from that of my Sex will convey my ſelf into your em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces. The love I bear you will not let you run the hazard of any danger, it being far from being poſſible. I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire your anſwer without delay, to th' end that I may govern my ſelf to your ſatisfaction, I being, both by election and obligation,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt humble Servant <hi>Felicia.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Characters did ſo deeply wound the Soul of the Count, that the leaſt part
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33822:34"/>
of his fury was to threaten death. Doubt and uncertainty could get no place in his mind, who by the Subſcription, by the Seal, and by the Hand-Writing was too much aſſured of his Wifes inconſtancy. He made ſuch imprecations againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Earth, and Himſelf with ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo vigorous as would have mov'd impiety it ſelf unto compaſſion. At length, conſidering that diſſimulation was the beſt means to facilitate his revenge, he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed haſtily into his Lodgings, and there tranſcribing his Wifes Letter, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting the hand, he Sealed it up and carried it back again to the place where he found it. Afterward, hiding himſelf at a convenient diſtance, as far as he could well ſee, he obſerved a Boy that came to take away that Letter; and a little after to bring thither another. He was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſee it, and found it, without Seal or Subſcription, to ſpeak theſe words:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Fair Lady,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Favours are then moſt to be priz'd, when they come leaſt expected. I would expreſs my thanks, if I could either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the Sentiments of my Soul unto my Pen, or could requite in any part, the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33822:35"/>
honour that is intended me. I will wait upon you that I may not be wanting to your ſatisfaction. I have no greater te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony at preſent of my love than to let you know that I can and will obey you. The hours will ſeem ages unto me, and I ſhall haſten every moment with a wiſh that I may the ſooner ſee you. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well my deareſt, my moſt beloved, and my faireſt one.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>M. O.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>The Count, being wholy poſſeſſed by rage and paſſion, and having his thoughts fixed on revenge, left the Letter in its place, and retired to his own Houſe. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the wanneſs of his face, and the wildneſs of his looks did diſcover the trouble of his mind; yet, covering his grief with a feigned ſmile, he ſaid he muſt go away preſently for the City, although the day before he had not appointed to go till after Dinner. <hi>Felicia</hi> did not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict him, but did rather give him ſome little buſineſs in charge, which might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him there the day following. Theſe were all accidents that did aggravate his Suſpicion, and did turn all his patience into fury. The Count went to the City
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33822:35"/>
attended by the greateſt part of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and afterwards came back with one only, of whoſe fidelity and courage he had had moſt experience. He arrived at the Village by Starlight; and, ſetting up his Horſes privately in one of the Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's Stables, he went to watch over the tranſactions at his own houſe. He had not ſtaid long before he heard the skreek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Door, and ſaw a Woman come out who, notwithſtanding the Garments ſhe had put on to diſguiſe her, was known by him. He thought her undoubtedly to be his Wife, but he would not ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf until he firſt ſaw whither ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned. He followed her, for to find out his diſhonourer and by his death, to revive his own reputation. She went not far but that ſhe was met and received, with open arms, by one who expected her. And although the darkneſs of the night did ſecure them from the curioſity of the eye; yet the kiſſes and careſſes of love were ſo many and ſo endearing, that they would have diſcovered the amorous theft even to thoſe to whom jealouſie had not lent an hundred eyes and as many ears. Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Prudence had no longer any power over the Counts fury. He thought
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33822:36"/>
it Stupidity and not Vertue to ſee others triumph in his diſhonour, and that even in his own preſence. Laying his hand therefore upon his Sword, with courage equal to his anger, he ſaid aloud, Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors can you ſo ſecurely ſtain the honour of a Gentleman? The tone of this voice being very well known by the Woman, did ſo fearfully aſtoniſh her, that ſhe had like to have fallen into a ſwoon. But her feet being winged with fear made her run ſpeedily avvay, vvhich fruſtrated the blovv the Count was giving with his Sword for to take away her life. The Man, on the other ſide, being as well vers'd in Martial, as Venereal Affairs, he being alſo enraged to ſee the courſe of his pleaſures interrupted (the variety of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man accidents perhaps not affording a greater provocation than this) betook himſelf to his Arms, with a courage not inferiour to the danger. And then he did ſo valiantly defend himſelf, and offend thoſe that ſet upon him, that although they were two, yet they could not hope for Victory without great hazard. The Fray did not laſt long, becauſe there came up ſix others in aſſiſtance to the lover; whereupon the Count (being forſaken by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33822:36"/>
his Servant) was forced to retire. The danger of his life was ſo apparent that it would have been raſhneſs, and not Valour to have fought againſt ſo much odds. It was eaſie for him to retreat, ſeeing thoſe men had no other end than to defend themſelves, and were not willing, by the ſlaughter of a Man they knew not, to run themſelves into the hands of Juſtice. The Count went thence to his own houſe ſo perplexed in mind, that deſperation was the leaſt effect of his paſſion. He had an intention to have chaſtiſed his Wife who had made her eſcape from him, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out endangering his life, and without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to diſcover the Murtherer of his Honour. The night, which for a few hours did caſt a Veil over his diſgraces, was about to uſher in the next day with ſo much the more ſhame, by hovv much he himſelf had partly been the author of it. To find out his Wife for to kill her was an hard matter, to find out her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for to revenge himſelf was perilous, and to cover his diſhonour was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Theſe conſiderations made him turn many times back with thoughts of loſing his life. He went ſearching about to no purpoſe, finding nothing but darkneſs,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33822:37"/>
and receiving no other anſwer to his calls than that of Ecchoes. He ſaid within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Fortune, vvhy didſt thou exalt me ſo much in giving me the Prerogatives of Riches and Nobility, thus for to precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate me into the abyſs of infamies which are the more grievous becauſe they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable? Perhaps you had no other means to exerciſe your fury upon me, than to wound my reputation, to blemiſh the honour of my houſe, and for ever to diſgrace my Poſterity. Whither, vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I go, to hide me from the ſcorn of thoſe vvho vvill triumph over my ſhame? I will fly from the City, I vvill fly all Converſation: I will fly the Sun, and I vviſh I could fly from my ſelf, that I might be far from remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that which, to my greater tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doth kill me in preſerving me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. In ſaying ſo he came near to the Walls of his own Houſe, when he ſaw ſome body that ſeem'd to watch there as a Spy; and certainly believing that there were the betrayers of his Honour, with a paſſionate and angry tone, he called out, Shall not the very Walls of my Houſe be ſecured from the perfidiouſneſs of thoſe that have raviſhed my honour? After your violat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33822:37"/>
my Wife, will you alſo violate my Walls by prying into my Secrets? It will be a little Satisfaction to my great loſſes for to ſacrifice thy life unto my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain. With theſe words he ran upon that Man who, that he might not be kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was forced to defend himſelf. The outcrys of the Aſſailant, and the aſſailed, did awake and raiſe up the People of the Houſe, who with Arms and Lights ran towards the noiſe. They came juſt in the nick, when the Count had his enemy under his feet, and was ready to take away his life. Seeing the light he ſtopp'd, for to ſee if he knew him, and found it was his Servant who, being fled from the firſt Quarrel, and yet fearful of his Maſters ſafety, return'd, with two Wounds, unto the Houſe. This ſight encreaſed the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Count who, ſtanding like a Statue, knew not what to command, nor what to reſolve upon. Whilſt he was in this irreſolution he obſerved, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out amazement, that his Wife, in a white Sarſenet Veil, was coming down the Stairs. He aſſuredly thought that ſhe vvas return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vvith an intention to deceive him. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurried therefore by that fury vvhich vvas enflamed vvith the ſence of honour,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33822:38"/>
(vvhile <hi>Felicia</hi> vvith great anxiety, did ask him hovv he did) he ran tovvard her vvith the Point of a Dagger ready to ſtrike her to the heart. Whether it vvere the overhſtily deſire of revenge, or the Will of God that deſires not the fall of the innocent, the blovv, paſſing only through her Garment, vvent under her Arm vvithout doing any further harm. The Count vvould have repeated his Blovvs, if the Maidens had not interpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in defence of their Miſtreſs. <hi>Felicia,</hi> proſtrating her ſelf on the ground, as vvell as her tears vvould give leave, ſaid unto him. Sir, What fault hath made the innocency of her guilty vvho hath remorſe of Conſcience for nothing more than for idolizing you? In theſe fevv hours that you have been abſent, I have ſinned in nothing but in praying for your ſafety. Pray Sir, let not malignity nor ſuſpicion give in teſtimony againſt my integrity, vvithout firſt hearing vvhat I have to ſay. Do not loſe, Sir, by inconſiderate paſſion the love of her, vvho if ſhe do not love you as much as you deſerve, yet ſhe loves you as much as ſhe can tell hovv to love an amiable thing. The Count, as it vvere yielding to her perſuaſion, being unvvill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33822:38"/>
to admit of any farther impediment to his reſolutions, raiſed her up and went with her into a Chamber, diſmiſſing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one elſe. There, taking the Poniard again into his hand, he ſpoke to <hi>Felicia,</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again proſtrate at his Feet, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, The colouring over of your perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs with a Lye cannot move me. You are guilty, and guilty of my diſhonour. Your accuſers are your own hands, and the Witneſſes are my own eyes. Your oppoſing the truth will be the encreaſing of your torment. Honour is a Goddeſs that cannot be appeas'd without a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Confeſs the violator of my Bed, and the Betrayer of your honeſty, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe this Weapon ſhall, by main force, extort the confeſſion from your mouth. My Lord, anſwered <hi>Felicia,</hi> if I were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of any thing but diſhoneſty, I ſhould dare to ſpeak in my defence, but in the matter of Honour I know not what to ſay. Grief checks my tongue, and tears do choak any words; Wherefore I can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay that I deſire my Men, Maids, and my Accuſers themſelves may be examin'd upon that point. In theſe I place my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, ſeeing that, from the time that you departed yeſterday, unto this very
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33822:39"/>
hour, being oppreſſed with grief of heart which preſaged unto me your anger, I went neither out of my Chamber, nor out of my Bed. <hi>Felicia</hi> accompanied theſe words with ſo many tears, that if they could not perſwade him, yet at leaſt they did ſerve to mitigate his diſpleaſure. He called in the Maid-Servants, and perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that one of them was wanting. The Count hereupon grew more jealous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that this was an Artifice of <hi>Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> and therefore drawing out the Letter, he ſaid unto her, if I ſhould believe this appearance of innocence, how wilt thou excuſe this Writing which convinceth thee of guiltineſs? Do not theſe black Characters point to thee the blackneſs of thy heart? Where will your boldneſs find pretences that can excuſe your diſhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty? <hi>Felicia</hi> took the Letter and obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it a little, cryed out, My Hand hath rebelled againſt my heart; as I cannot deny to have written it, ſo I cannot confeſs to have indicted it. O God my very eyes are deceived in believing that to be my act which is but only like mine. The Count's fury was hereat revived, when a Letter was preſented him from a Coſen of his which, becauſe it came by an expreſs, did
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33822:39"/>
require a ſpeedy anſwer. The Count, opening it, found it contained theſe words:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Dear Coſen,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>This very Night my Siſter <hi>Felicia</hi> went out of my Houſe in Mans Habit. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I have no certainty of her deſign, yet I ſuſpect ſhe is gone aſide to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Odorico.</hi> Pray let it be your care to ſearch out the truth, ſince your inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy with the Marqueſs will facilitate this buſineſs. I would have come my ſelf if my old indiſpoſition, receiving a new addition by this accident had not neceſſitated me to keep my Bed. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the more haſte, becauſe it is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Honour.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>The Count of <hi>Caſtello.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>This Letter aſſwaged the fury of the Count, he being thereby aſſured of his Wifes honeſty, and the vanity of his own ſuſpicions, ſeeing the Letter was writ by her Coſen, and the likeneſs of Hands did ariſe from their having both learnt to write by one and the ſame Maſter. He
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33822:40"/>
was the more ſenſible of his errour when he was aſcertain'd by all that <hi>Felicia</hi> had not been out of her Bed, and that the Maid-Servant was gone out to meet her Sweet-heart. And he was ſo much the more confirmed herein, becauſe the love that paſſed between his Coſin and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs was very well known in thoſe parts. Perceiving therefore that the ſame Name, and the ſame Character were the cauſes of his miſtake, embracing his Wife, he begg'd her excuſe for having, for the ſake of his Honour, treated her with terms unworthy of her Affection and Fidelity.</p>
               <p>This may be an example to thoſe that take the meer ſhadows of things for the very bodies themſelves; and may warn Husbands not to precipitate themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe reſolutions which carry with them the hazard of their Lives and good Names, ſeeing that Jealouſie is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive both the Eyes, and other the Senſes.</p>
               <p>It may alſo teach Wives to be vigilant over their Maidens, ſince their diſhoneſty doth often reflect upon the reputation of their Miſtreſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="novel">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:33822:40"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eudoſia</hi> doth ſeverely cenſure and watch over the love-motions of her Daughter <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cella.</hi> And, finding a Love-Letter in her hand, is enamoured of her Lover, whom ſhe inviteth to ly with her, feigning her ſelf to be <hi>Dercella.</hi> But being deceived by another, ſhe giveth her Daughter the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of enjoying her own, whereupon both of them are Married.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVELL</hi> VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>doſia</hi> being the Daughter of the Count of <hi>Vancaſtro,</hi> was ſo rich in the Endowments of Mind, Body and Fortune, that ſhe ſcarce attained the Age of Thirteen, before ſhe had rais'd up pretenſions in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to aſpire to the poſſeſſion of her. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the great Riches of her Father did move the Avarice of ſome Men to obtain her to Wife, yet the excellence of her Beauty did tyrannically preſide over the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33822:41"/>
affections of all: for ſhe, being favoured by all the Graces, was thought not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to them in any thing, but their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>Evander</hi> the Nobleſt, but withall the Eldeſt of all her Sutors, had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to gain this Heavenly Beauty. The Fate of theſe <hi>Aurora's</hi> betrothing them moſt commonly unto <hi>Titons.</hi> This Match ſeemed ſtrange in the eyes of the World, <hi>Evander</hi> being deemed more fit for his Grave, than for the Nuptial Bed. He was in the Fifty Third Year of his Age; wherefore by the Wrinckles of his Brows and the greyneſs of his Hairs, they thought the union of ſo fair a Spring with rugged Winter, that bore no fruit but what was harſh and ſower, to be impracticable. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſia,</hi> being very young and knowing no better, did eaſily comply with the embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of an old Man, eſteeming the chiefeſt happineſs of her Marriage to conſiſt in the richneſs of her Cloths, the variety of Jewels, the abundance of Gold, the great number of Servants, and in the conſtant aſſiſtance of her Husband who, becoming jealous of her, did think her loſt, as oft as ſhe was out of his ſight. This conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual attendance of <hi>Evander</hi> did oblige him to ſome employments that were greater
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33822:41"/>
than the ſtrength of his age could bear; whereupon the Nuptials were ſcarce end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when his Funerals did begin. The death of <hi>Evander</hi> was accompanied with ſuch lively ſentiments of grief in his Wife, that weeping, wailing and ſighing were the leaſt arguments of her ſorrow. She would have been buried even alive with him, if the knowledge of her being with Child had not flatter'd her with the hopes of reviving him in bearing a Son. But her deſire was fruſtrated by the Birth of a Daughter who, even in her Cradle, did oblige her beholders to form excellent conceits of her Beauty. <hi>Eudoſia</hi> would not hearken, much leſs adhere to any more overtures of Marriage; ſhe believing that no man living could make her ſo happy as <hi>Evander</hi> had done. She voluntarily confined her ſelf to her Houſe attending to the education of her Daughter, but in ſo ſtrict a manner that ſhe was near Thirteen Years old, and could not boaſt either to have ſeen, or have been ſeen by any Men except thoſe that waited on her Mother. She went not abroad above two or three times a Year, and then ſo veiled and guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as if they feared the Air ſhould raviſh her. Her apartment ſcarce gave any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33822:42"/>
to the bright Eye of Heaven, much leſs to the Eyes of any mortal Men; and then the continual Guardianſhip of her Mother did not permit her to uſe any other divertiſement than ſome Childiſh Paſtimes. Fortune, who commonly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes for Lovers, brought it ſo about that <hi>Eudoſia</hi> and <hi>Dercella</hi> (for this was the Daughters name) were, by ſome great out-crys which did ſtir up their curioſity by being very violent, forcibly drawn to look out at the Window. They ſaw the life of their Neighbour <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by many Swords encompaſſing him, whilſt that he did defend himſelf with a Courage greater than his Years. The Youth and handſome Shape of <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> did quickly move <hi>Eudoſia</hi> to pity: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, by commanding her Servants to bring him into the Houſe, ſhe deliver'd him out of the hands of thoſe Cut-throats who, having wounded him in the hand, and deeply in the Side, were very near to have murther'd him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> after ſome few Complements, accepted the invitation of going to Bed. Here, his Mother being called, he attended the recovery of his Health, the Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not permitting him to go out of that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33822:42"/>
houſe, for fear that the Air and Motion might exaſperate his Wounds. <hi>Dercella,</hi> although ſhe never knew, nor ſo much as heard of the Name of Love, yet was ſo much ſurprized at the firſt ſight of <hi>Aſſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> that ſhe fell in love before ſhe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it. And not being able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the firſt ſhock, ſhe ſometimes liſtned to the diſcourſes of the Phyſicians; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhe inquired how he did of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and at other times, though often reproved by her Mother, ſhe came into his Chamber making many excuſes for to ſee him. The night did more increaſe the troubles of her mind which, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated by confuſed thoughts, could take no reſt. And if ſometimes ſhe ſhut her eyes, being weary with watching, yet was ſhe preſently forced to open them again, for to avoid thoſe fantaſms that did tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment her ſleeping, more than waking. <hi>Dercella</hi> continued for the ſpace of ſome days in theſe amorous frenzies, until ſuch time as <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> being pretty well recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, went away to his own Houſe. He had ſeveral times obſerved ſome glances proceeding from the eyes of that Maiden which were rather witneſſes of affection than of compaſſion: but, not being well
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33822:43"/>
vers'd in Love-Affairs, he condemned all thoſe thoughts, as idle ſuſpicions, that might have perſwaded him to have been beloved. Yet being kindled by the ſparks of that Beauty which might make all boldneſs excuſable, he ſtaying at home for the perfect confirmation of his Health, was continually looking out at a Window that anſwered to <hi>Dercellas</hi> apartment. Here he was eaſily diſcovered by her who, being hurried by a thouſand impatient affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, did deſire nothing more than to ſee him. Having found a way to open a Window directly oppoſite to that of her Lover, and which her jealous Mother had on purpoſe kept ſhut: She had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſeeing him at her pleaſure, but not of ſpeaking to him, either becauſe of her own modeſty, or for fear of her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers jealouſie. He likewiſe, being ſtruck dumb by an exceſs of love, did, by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of his eyes, perform all the offices of his tongue. At laſt, overcoming all difficulties, he breathed out his paſſions by writing in this manner:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The love that forcibly tyeth up my tongue with the ſame violence moveth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33822:43"/>
now my hand, and compels me to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplifie the Vaſſallage of my heart, which is already contracted and confirmed to you by my eyes. Indeed force hath been very requiſite for to oblige me to make a declaration which, in regard of your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent merit, cannot be termed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than raſh. Beauty which is the Ray of Divine Light, will not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed in the vulgar terms of humanity. I know it very well, but can't tell how to help it. Accept, fair Lady, of theſe expreſſions which come from a ſoul that glories more in your dominion, than in its own proper being. Vouchſafe me an anſwer in favour of thoſe hopes which only are able to keep alive</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt devoted and obliged Servant <hi>Aſſirdus.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>He eaſily conveyed this Letter into the hands of <hi>Dercella;</hi> for, watching the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of her looking out at Window, he gently darted it into her Boſom. This Virgin being as curious as loving, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly took leave to read it. While her ſoul was raviſhed with the delight of theſe Characters, ſhe was not aware of her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33822:44"/>
ſeeing of her, who did every minute make the actions of her daughter ſubject both to her obſervation and cenſure. The firſt thing <hi>Eudoſia</hi> did was to tear the Letter out of her hand; loading her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards with ſo many reproaches and menaces, that ſighs and tears were the leaſt burthen of <hi>Dercellas</hi> affliction. But the loſs of that Paper, that ſeemed to prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate the loſs of all her love and hopes, was that which moſt troubled her. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſia,</hi> leaving her drowned in tears, went into another Room for to read the Letter, and to find out how ſhe came by it. And as ſoon as ſhe ſaw it came from <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> ſhe felt a ſtrange commotion in her mind. His Youth and Beauty made way for her deſire to get him to her ſelf. She began to repent of having ſpent ſo many years without enjoyment. She thought all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſures, except thoſe that proceed from Conjugal Love, to be but flaſhy. On the other ſide ſhe feared the cenſure of the World in retarding a reſolution for the ſpace of thirteen Years. She was afraid of the raſhneſs of her daughter; of the tender age of <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> and did conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that to Marry a ſecond time, after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo long mourned for her firſt Husband,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33822:44"/>
would but expoſe her to the imputation of Fame for wilfully loſing her liberty. But our affections being moſtly governed by ſence, ſhe reſolved to venture the loſs of all rather than to loſe the love of <hi>Aſſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</hi> Wherefore, taking a Pen in Hand, ſhe wrote, in her daughters name, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Aſſirdus,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>She that yields at the firſt Onſet, doth greatly ſhew her own weakneſs, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape the diſrepute of Cowardize. Nevertheleſs they that love well cannot at all diſſemble. Love is a fire which by how much the more it is ſuppreſſed, by ſo much the more it is enkindled. I do therefore hereby declare unto you, that I love you heartily, and if I had not been afraid of being denyed, I would have firſt ſued for your love. Therefore if you have a mind to enter with me into the lawful eſtate of Matrimony, I do expect you this Night at the Garden-door which you will find only ſhut to. Otherwiſe your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are illegitimate, and will be very far from any hopes of enjoying</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Dercella.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33822:45"/>This Letter being privately delivered into the hands of <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> inſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing him, did ſtir up ſuch a confuſion in his thoughts that they robbed him of his quiet. Were it either the little experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he had in Love-affairs, or his ſeeing the poſſeſſion of that Beauty (which he ſo much the more prized, by how much the more difficulty he apprehended in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it) ſo freely offered unto him, he confeſſed himſelf a penitent for having gone ſo far. Whilſt he was thus irreſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and doubtful, the Count of <hi>Bell'om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> a young Gentleman of High Birth, though of low Fortune, came to ſee him. At firſt ſight he diſcover'd ſome paſſion in <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> whereupon he very earneſtly preſſed him to tell the occaſion. <hi>Aſſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> being as eaſie to diſcover his diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances, as to be diſturbed, told this Count all the motives that troubled his mind, praying him, as a friend, to give him his beſt advice. The Count perceiving that this might be an occaſion of advancing his own condition, being willing to take her to himſelf that Fortune offered to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, perſuaded <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> not to venture upon the raſh invitation of a Girl more worthy to be ſlighted than beloved, ſeeing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33822:45"/>
that ſhe did ſo eaſily proſtitute het ſelf to the pleaſure of a Lover. That the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of a preſuppoſed Husband by Night was a manifeſt token of her having enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained others. That he, not well foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the danger, might run the hazard of being trepann'd if, by following his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual appetite, he ſhould accept of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation. To theſe he added ſo many other conſiderations, that being joyned to the averſion <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> had in himſelf, made him reſolve wholly to quit the enterprize, and ſo much the rather becauſe his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would very hardly have given him leave to go abroad. A little after the Count, upon pretence of ſome buſineſs, taking his leave, went at night to the Garden-Gate of <hi>Eudoſia</hi> who, believing him to be <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> received him with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Arms; he alſo being no leſs deceived in ſuppoſing her to be <hi>Dercella,</hi> after ſome ſhort Complements in a very low voice, as fearful of being overheard, they retir'd, without any light, into a Ground-chamber where, upon a very rich Couch, they gave place to one anothers amorous embraces. In the mean time <hi>Dercella,</hi> believing her Mother to be immers'd in ſleep, and not in pleaſures, roſe out of her hated, becauſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33822:46"/>
reſtleſs Bed, and went to the Window juſt in the nick when <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> being no leſs diſquieted, came thither alſo. <hi>Dercella</hi> did ſend forth frequent ſighs, both for the injuries received of her Mother, and becauſe ſo unlucky a beginning made her wiſh to ſee the end of her love. <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> perſuading himſelf that thoſe ſighs did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from the default of his Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, enforcing himſelf, ſaid, Lady, I know not which to blame moſt either my bad fortune, or my little merit that make me unworthy to partake of the favours of Love. <hi>Dercella,</hi> believing that he did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid her not correſponding with him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, Love overcomes all difficulties, and if it acts unlike it ſelf in me, I muſt blame my Fate that makes me love without hope. There is no love without hope, anſwer'd he, ſeeing the latter is the very ſubſtance of the former. And what (ſaid he) would you have me hope, when all things conſpire to make me deſpair? Why then, replied he, is not reciprocal love ſufficient to give you true content? But who, added ſhe, can give me aſſurance hereof? ſince the promiſes and words of Lovers are commonly accounted but Wind. I, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> by dedicating my ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33822:46"/>
your ſervice. Theſe, ſaid <hi>Dercella,</hi> are words which are ſoon diſſolv'd into the ſame air whereof they are formed. I would give you the proof of them, replied he, if I thought you would not condemn my raſhneſs. And what would you do, ſaid ſhe? I would, with the help of a Plank, anſwered he, come over to your Chamber, there to conclude our Loves, and ſave my heart from the Rack of hopes and fears. Hereupon <hi>Dercella</hi> pauſed a little, as if ſhe were afraid either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, or receive this offer, and then ſaid ſhe I cannot ſo ſuddenly take any reſolution, upon a propoſal of ſo great a conſequence. He, who by the power of Love had caſt off all fear, and put on a courage which was augmented by ſeeing himſelf exceſſively beloved, replied, He that uſes overmuch circumſpection is not in love, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of no long conſultations, for that all delays, eſpecially in amorous affairs, are dangerous. Here is no <hi>medium,</hi> either you muſt give your aſſent, or confeſs you do not love me. <hi>Dercella</hi> anſwered, although I cannot expreſs the deſire I have to be yours; yet I will never conſent that you paſs out of your Window into mine, that I may not at once ſee both my Reputation
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33822:47"/>
and your life endangered. <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon theſe expreſſions to be rather conſenting than diſſenting, placing a Board on <hi>Dercellas</hi> Window, went over there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon into her Chamber. Here after ſome ſlight reproofs and feigned repulſes which ſerved inſtead of ſo many invitations, <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cella,</hi> being overcome by his importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, gave him leave to reap that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which is moſt grateful to Lovers.</p>
               <p>In this interim <hi>Eudoſia</hi> had given, in ſome part, ſatisfaction to the provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſenſe when, fearing that her actions might be diſcovered, ſhe left the Count aſleep, and went ſoftly to viſit all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of her Houſe. At laſt ſhe came to her Daughters Chamber juſt as the Lovers, by a murmuring prologue of kiſſes, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to act a loving Comedy. It ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtrange that her Daughter, in ſo tender an age, ſhould dare encounter the arms of a Lover. Yet, being perſwaded that the errors of Love deſerved compaſſion, and knowing her ſelf to be guilty of the ſame fault, ſhe reſolved to diſſemble that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for not to diſcover her own. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe had a mind to know her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Sweet-heart, to ſee if the worthineſs of her choice did make any amends for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33822:47"/>
the boldneſs of her attempt. Scarce did ſhe caſt her Eye upon <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> but, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be her own Lover, ſhe gave her ſelf wholly up to Fury like one poſſeſt with a Legion of Devils. She ſcratched her face, tore her hair, beat her breaſt, and did all things that might ſhew her rage, and expreſs her grief. Laſtly, with railing and reproachful language ſhe uttered her paſſion ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Perfidious man! after having enjoyed the Mother art thou come alſo to betray the innocency of my Daughter? Why did Nature and Fortune make this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Traytor ſo amiable? Are theſe the promiſes you made me but even now? Does this Treachery confirm your Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity? Oh Heavens! I ſhall believe you ſtand ſtill, and that your influences are blind, if you do not dart your Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts at this impious Villain.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dercella</hi> hearing theſe words of her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thinking ſhe was impoſed upon by <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> fell a weeping, and with ſuch lively expreſſions of grief, as would have ſoftned the hardeſt heart, ſhe ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Why, O Cruel Man, haſt thou betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a poor, ſimple and innocent Girl? Why haſt thou deceived me by a piece of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33822:48"/>
Treachery which is the more execrable, for having been hid under the Mask of Love? Where, where, O inhumane Wretch, haſt thou learnt ſuch unnatural Cruelty, that even ſavage Beaſts are not guilty of. Pray Mother pardon that raſhneſs which did not think, by its Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, of offending the Laws of Nature, nor the ſatisfaction of her that gave me my being.</q>
               </p>
               <p>She would have gone in if <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> who hitherto had been as immoveable as a Stock, had not interrupted her, ſaying, <hi>Dercella,</hi> Whoſoever doubts of my Fidelity, may as well doubt of her own Senſibility. I do declare my ſelf yours, and offer my ſelf ready to confirm my declaration by a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Marriage, which ſhall be no longer in effecting than you are in conſenting. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſia</hi> was much more enraged at theſe words, whereupon, redoubling her out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crys, ſhe furiouſly ran to ſatisfie her anger by the force of her hands. <hi>Dercella,</hi> love not permitting her to ſee <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without defending him, interpoſed for to pacifie her Mother; but ſhe, growing more and more outragious, was near upon ſome miſchievous reſolution, if the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33822:48"/>
appearing of the Count had not ſtaid her and ſtruck her dumb. He had impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, for ſome time, waited the return of his beloved, but not ſeeing her come, he went out of the Chamber to ſeek her; not without fear that this her ſtaying might portend ſome diſaſter. As ſoon as he heard the out-crys his fears were increaſed, ſo that he came haſtily in where <hi>Eudoſia,</hi> by ſcratching and biting, was giving vent to her furious paſſion.</p>
               <p>They were all amazed at this appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the Count was much aſtoniſhed at the ſight of <hi>Aſſirdus;</hi> whereupon <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſia</hi> began to ask him how he got into the Houſe. To which the Count anſwered, by the invitation of <hi>Dercella.</hi> Thou ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ſaid ſhe; and except <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> there's no man can brag of having my love. The lye, replied he, from a Girl, makes no matter; and the rather, becauſe this Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth declare you guilty. In ſaying ſo, he drew forth a Letter, and being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to read it, he was interrupted by <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> who ſpake unto him, O unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful friend, this Letter belongs to me. It is true, added the Count, but you refuſing to come hither, I ſupplied your place, and have enjoyed her with a promiſe of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33822:49"/>
Then, anſwered <hi>Aſſirdus,</hi> ſhall <hi>Dercella</hi> have two Husbands? I alſo having enjoyed her by the ſame promiſe. <hi>Eudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> now perceiving that, whilſt ſhe went about to deceive others, ſhe her ſelf was deceived and, being unwilling that the publication of this accident ſhould be an occaſion of Town-talk, ſpoke thus to the Count and to <hi>Aſſirdus.</hi> Sirs, if you will, as becomes Gentlemen, keep to your words of Marriage, I will ſee that you ſhall have the ſame perſons that you have enjoyed. For my part, ſaid the Count, I do think my ſelf honoured in confirming what I promiſed. <hi>Aſſirdus</hi> ſaid the ſame; yet were they both very much concerned, knowing that <hi>Dercella</hi> could be Wife but to one of them. The wonder ceaſed when <hi>Eudoſia</hi> diſcovered that ſhe was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Letter, and had ſubmitted to the Count, ſuppoſing him to be <hi>Aſſirdus.</hi> The Count, who had no greater end than to enrich himſelf: and therefore made no diſtinction between the Mother and the Daughter, ſhew'd himſelf well contented. And hereupon the Weddings were cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated with extraordinary Mirth and Jollity: Giving to underſtand, that who ſo keep themſelves within the bounds of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33822:49"/>
honeſty, may always expect a good end to be the conſequent of their juſt deſires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="novel">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arſinda,</hi> being left a Widdow, promiſes to marry the Count of <hi>Rocca Battuta.</hi> But, being cozened with a Letter counterfeited by the Marqueſs <hi>Odorico,</hi> ſhe refuſeth the former, and makes a Contract with the latter. At length, the fraud being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by one of her Maidens, ſhe will not have the Marqueſs, but haſtneth away to celebrate the Counts Funeral whom ſhe believed to be dead. Yet finding him alive, and being followed by the Marqueſs, they all come to an untimely end.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVEL</hi> VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARſinda,</hi> who in the City of <hi>Lisbon</hi> was Miſtreſs of all thoſe Prerogatives that do make an accompliſht Woman, having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een two years marry'd, was left to bewail <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he fatal cutting of that Knot which ſhe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33822:50"/>
wiſhed might never have been looſned. But although ſhe did, with admirable expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſorrow, honour the exequies of her Husband, yet it was not long before ſhe repented the ſacrificing of ſo many tears to thoſe unhappy aſhes, and perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf that they were but vain kind of demonſtrations which, being derided of all thoſe that obſerved them, did hurt to the living, and no good to the dead. Hearkning therefore to the incitements of ſenſe, and the propoſals of her Relations who invited her to marry again, ſhe tyed her heart, no leſs than her word to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letes</hi> the Count of <hi>Rocca Battuta.</hi> And although Women do many times err in their choice, yet ſhe was eſteemed the more prudent and vertuous for chuſing a Gentleman that was ſo excellently well qualified.</p>
               <p>The Nuptials were concluded on by the authority of thoſe that had moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over them, and <hi>Arſinda,</hi> making uſe of that liberty which is uſual with Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, did one day privately introduce the Count into her Garden, there to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs that content which ſhe now began inwardly to enjoy. At this meeting there was no demonſtration either of love
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33822:50"/>
or reſpect wanting. The Count did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare how much he was honoured in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preferred before others: and <hi>Arſinda</hi> extolled his merit which had conſtrained her to make him ſole owner of her heart. While they were thus contending with theſe affectionate declarations, there came in a Page who delivered a Letter into the hands of <hi>Arſinda.</hi> She, not ſo much as looking upon the Seal, with a loving con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, gave it to the Count. He, receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it very courteouſly, opened it, and ſaw that, without any ſubſcription, it ſaid thus,
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Fair Lady,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Your excuſes are more courtly, than neceſſary, and I am more fit to receive, than to deſerve your favours. I know that experience doth aſſure me of your affection, but my heart, being jealous even of its own deſires, doth ſigh to ſee this day, which not only denys me, but communicates unto another thoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are (not mine, though I am) permitted to enjoy them. I ſhould be afraid that the juſt title of the Count would condemn my poſſeſſion as tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical (I being but a paramour) if the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33822:51"/>
power of the Will did not ſurpaſs that of the Law. Do not, O fair one, in company of your Spouſe, loſe the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Gallant, who is more deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your love, becauſe leſs deſiring to impoſe upon you the ties of Matrimony, and whoſe ambition is not to be your companion, but your ſervant.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>The Count made an end of reading this Letter with many ſigns of impatience, which brought ſuch a confuſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful thoughts into <hi>Arſindas</hi> mind that ſhe became ſpeechleſs. The bloud fluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into her face, not to ſhew any guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but that it might not ſuffocate her heart which, by a greater palpitation than ordinary, did ſhew the reſentments due to the raſhneſs of that Paper. The Count, taking this ſilence for a confeſſion of her fault, with an odious, becauſe feigned ſmile that began and ended in the ſame minute, ſaid unto her, <hi>Madam,</hi> Your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Marriage to me was needleſs, ſince (for ought I underſtand) Gallants are more pleaſing to you than Husbands. Theſe words making <hi>Arſinda</hi> to reflect more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her own innocency, than upon the Counts jealouſie, ſhe did not ſuffer him to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33822:51"/>
ſay any more but, with a no leſs free, than ſcornful behaviour, after many ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, ſhe even told him he himſelf was the Author of that Letter. And, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking leave, ſhe retired into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, leaving the mind of the Count cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly tormented between Love and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie. The Count therefore ſuppoſing that the expreſſions of <hi>Arſinda</hi> were the more feigned, for being ſo vehement, and not being able to induce in himſelf a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of her innocency, he let himſelf fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of deſperation; his anger being arrived at that pitch that he could no longer endure her either as a Miſtreſs, or an enemy. Without mentioning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to any body the madneſs of his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, he took Horſe and departed from the City, hating all thoſe things which might reduce to his memory the infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her, whom he was forc'd to adore, though he thought her inconſtant. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried on more ſwiftly by the rage of deſpair, than by the Speed of his Horſe, the night approaching, he was conſtrained to take ſhelter in an Inn. Here, with no leſs hatred to himſelf, than to the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of others, neglecting to beſpeak any Supper, he ſhut himſelf into a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33822:52"/>
alone, with an intent there to give vent to, rather than allay the fierceneſs of his paſſion. Being alone he abandoned himſelf up to ſorrow, to th'end that, by by the Streams of his eyes, he might, in ſome meaſure disburthen the overflowing oppreſſion of his heart. At length, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weary of Solemnizing, with a Deluge of tears, the Funeral of his hopes, he thought of raiſing himſelf from miſery, by humbling himſelf before that Idol, whoſe diſpleaſure brought more terrour to his ſoul than any other ſort of chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So, taking Pen in hand he wrote as follows:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Fair Lady,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The heart is not ſubject to the faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trings of the tongue; and repentance is the amendment of errors. In confidence whereof my deſires are flatter'd with the hopes of finding you to day as compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, as yeſterday I found you cruel. I beſeech you therefore, O Fair One, to bury in oblivion the extravagant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions of a poor ſoul that did doat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the raviſhing delights of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; and be pleas'd to re-eſtabliſh me in your affection, which will be the more
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33822:52"/>
dear unto me, becauſe I having moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt it, you may the more graciouſly reſtore it unto me. Altho I could excuſe my fault, yet I do freely confeſs it for to give the greater merit to your pardon, whereof my raſhneſs had made me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy. Upon this ſovereign act of your benignity doth depend the life of</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt devoted and obliged Servant <hi>Rocca Battuta.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Recommending this Letter to the Hoſt both for its delivery, and for an anſwer, he returned to his former affliction, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what effects his Writing might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. Whilſt, by tormenting thoughts, he felt the Tyranny both of hope and fear, he heard a mournful noiſe made by ſome ſorrowful perſon. Being a little comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe doleful tones, and applying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers unhappineſs as a Plaiſter to his own Wounds, he drew near to a Partition of Boards that divided the Room. There he heard one ſpeak ſome words indiſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which did blame Love and Fortune as the authors of his oppreſſion. It now ſeemed that his paſſion was alleviated by the mixture of another's misfortune, when
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33822:53"/>
a little after there came into the Chamber, whence theſe ſorrowful complaints did proceed, a Man crying out, Victory, my Lord Marqueſs <hi>Odorico,</hi> Victory. By my ingenuity <hi>Rocca Battuta</hi> is wholly batter'd down, and you to morrow ſhall take poſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſion of <hi>Arſinda,</hi> theſe Nuptials ſtaying for nothing but your arrival in the City. The Marqueſs who, by exceeding pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, had repelled his grief, could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the aſſaults of theſe joyful tydings. He cryed out like a Mad-man in conceits ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive of his great content. Why then (ſaid he) ſhall <hi>Arſinda</hi> be mine? Is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that I ſhall be the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> of that amorous Heaven which ſent forth nothing but lightnings to ſet fire on my faithful affection? O Fortune! I will offer Sacrifices to thy honour. O God of Love I thank thee. And if heretofore I have raſhly offended the ſovereignty of thy power, I do now repent me of it, ſince that <hi>Arſinda</hi> is to be mine. The Count being out of all patience, and not conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that theſe accidents might carry him to ſome precipice, with a loud voice he made himſelf to be heard in theſe terms. Traitors, your Treachery is diſcover'd and, if Heaven doth not favour injuſtice, or if
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33822:53"/>
my Sword hath not loſt its edge, ſhall be puniſhed. In uttering theſe words he ran furiouſly into the Hall with his Sword naked in his hand, while the Marqueſs with equal fury came to meet him. Here they began a duel with all the rage that hatred and jealouſie could infuſe into them. The Count, with a few blows, would have worſted the Marqueſs, if two Souldiers of his had not interpoſed in his defence. The Fight being ſo unequal, the Count was neceſſitated to take his life as a gift from them, although his generous mind ſcorn'd to ask it, and his paſſionate heart abhorred to receive it. Being deeply wounded in two places he was, by the Inn-keeper, recommended to the Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons; whilſt he, diſdaining to live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his beloved, and hating to ſee her in the poſſeſſion of his enemy, thought there was no more proper remedy for his grief, than deſpair. The anguiſh of his wounds was much exaſperated by the anſwer of <hi>Arſinda</hi> which, coming from a Lady that generouſly inſiſted upon her honour, did bring nothing but the expreſſions of an alienated affection, and implacable averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Her Letter ſpake in this manner:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="104" facs="tcp:33822:54"/>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>He that has the heart to injure a Lady of honour, may alſo have the courage to endure her reſentments. Thus much I thought good to intimate unto you, more for the ſake of good manners, than for your deſerts. I am ſorry I cannot adjuſt the deſires of my heart to the weakneſs of my Sex, thereby to chaſtiſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions of a tongue no leſs raſh, than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous. Do not abuſe my patience by any more Letters; for, if you do, reſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that they, being burnt into aſhes, will the longer preſerve the moſt juſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain of</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Arſinda.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>This Letter, being indiſcreetly given into the hands of the Count at a time when, being very ill of his late hurts and a Feaver that attended them, but much more languiſhing under the oppreſſion of his mind, it cauſed ſuch a deſperate alteration in him, that his attendants thought him to be upon the point of Death. He did often aggravate his mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by lamentable exclamations which no man could hear without commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:33822:54"/>Whilſt he was ſtrugling with the ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of death being given over both by Chyrurgions and Phyſicians, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs was enjoying the Viſits and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulations of his Friends and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. With theſe he boaſted of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful ingenuity in fraudulently and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly ſubduing a Womans heart, which commonly (he ſaid) was termed the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeat of Artifice and Deceit. Hereupon he was requeſted to trace the ſucceſs of his amours from the beginning. To this he moſt readily aſſented in ſaying thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Sirs, I do willingly repeat the tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of my love, becauſe the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them ſeems ſweet unto me. I did, a good while ſince, ſet my whole affection upon <hi>Arſinda,</hi> but very unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully, becauſe Women do not ſo much correſpond with their Lovers, as with the capricious humor of their own Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius. They love not him that deſerveth beſt, but him that complieth beſt with their imperfections; ſo that it is e'en become a Proverbial Saying, <hi>That the choice of Women ordinarily falls upon the worſt.</hi> In ſhort I was rejected, and <hi>Rocca Battuta</hi> was the man pitcht upon for a Husband, with that reſentment
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33822:55"/>
which may better be imagined than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. Seeing the merits of my Birth and Love excluded, I had recourſe unto Stratagems that are no leſs neceſſary in Love, than in Arms. Thus I got the Victory; for <hi>Rocca Battuta,</hi> being cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by my counterfeit Letter, quitted the Field, and left me alone to triumph.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words were overheard by a Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to whom <hi>Arſinda</hi> confided all her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, who by chance came then to the Marqueſs his houſe for to complement him from her Miſtreſs. The Damſel would not ſtay to hearken any more, knowing very well that <hi>Arſinda</hi> had condeſcended to this Marriage more in obedience to the impulſes of anger, than in compliance to the inclinations of her heart. She there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpeedily ran away to <hi>Arſinda,</hi> to whom ſhe imparted what ſhe had heard from the Marqueſs <hi>Odorico</hi>'s own mouth. Here I am at a ſtand, for to expreſs the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Arſinda's</hi> mind. She grew pale, dumb, wept, and did all things incident to a ſoul overwhelmed with paſſion and grief. She had condemn'd her ſelf to marry the Marqueſs, only to revenge the injuries of the Count, and for fear that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33822:55"/>
what had paſſed betwixt him and her might hinder her Fortunes; for ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had a great averſion to the Marqueſs for that he was not only ill-favoured, but alſo ill-natur'd. And now, that ſhe knew him to be treacherous, her hatred was grown to that height, that ſhe could not endure to hear his Name, much leſs to ſee him. Preferring therefore ſatisfaction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other intereſt, ſhe took Pen and Ink and wrote thus:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>To deceive the deceiver is no deceit. For this reaſon I recant all thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes I made to be yours. I never thought of being ſtolen away, nor ſhall your treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery triumph over my ſimplicity. Yet you may believe that my eyes do, by ſhowr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down tears, ſtrive to clear up the cloudineſs of my ſoul, which would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (if poſſible) loſe its being, than ever conſent to the tying of a knot that was contrived by fraud, and not by love. Do not provoke me by any new guiles, leſt you turn my patience into fury. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you may be caught in your own gins, and may feel what effects the moſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33822:56"/>
juſt reſentment of a Woman unjuſtly off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ended can produce.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Arſinda.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſent this Letter to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, ſhe began to revolve in her mind the ſatisfactions due to the Count, when one of her Maids preſented her a Letter, ſaying that it was brought by a Page to the Count, who, being upon his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this World, could neither make an end of it, nor ſeal it. She took it with great eagerneſs, and ſaw that the Contents were as follow:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I make uſe of another hand becauſe my own is not able to govern a Pen. Excuſe me <hi>Arſinda,</hi> it proceeding from weakneſs, and not from want of reſpect in me. I dye, and dye unhappily in that I am deprived of your gracious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. If my aſhes could obtain the leaſt affectionate pity, I believe it would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert thoſe horrors that are preached up to be moſt terrible, into happineſs. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him, O fair Lady, who can never offend you more, and who did offend you more to obey the exceſs of his love,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33822:56"/>
than to bring any prejudice to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. But my Speech failing me makes me uncapable of pleading any farther in my own defence. I dye <hi>Arſinda,</hi> and I dye for you; having nothing more to add to theſe characters but my ſighs for to ſoften the heart of <hi>Arſinda.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arſinda</hi> had ſcarce run over the Letter but, letting it fall from her hands, ſhe alſo, not being able to reſiſt the violence of a grief that ſo ſenſibly ſtruck to her heart, fell into a Swoon. Being brought to life again by ſome remedies that her Maidens applied, ſhe thus began to bemoan her ſelf:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>O God! is it poſſible that I ſhould not ſink under the weight of inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſorrow? How can my ſoul, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by ſuch fierce paſſions, do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than abandon me? Thoſe torments are but ſlight that do not kill. And yet my grief, which is upon the very brink of deſperation, is not able to take away my life. Couldſt thou my beloved <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letes,</hi> poiſoned by my unjuſt diſdain, dye? and cannot I, at the doleful news of thy death, and the craft of a Traitor, leave off to live? There is not a more precious
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33822:57"/>
thing in the World than a faithful man, and I have loſt him before I knew him. But to what purpoſe do I aggravate my ſorrows, by uſurping thoſe tears that are moſt juſtly due to his Hearſe. Yes, yes, I am reſolved at leaſt to pay my laſt office to the greatneſs of his Merits, and my obligations; and they that ſee the dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fects of it ſhall not condemn me. Away with all delay. Let's go to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him dying, whom we deſpiſed living.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore calling for her Coach, ſhe went, with all the ſpeed imaginable, along with him that brought the Letter, unto the Inn where the Count was lodged: as if ſhe were reſolved to join her ſelf to him in the Grave, ſince that Fortune had denied her a more deſirable union. As ſoon as ſhe was alighted from her Coach, ſhe was preſently conducted (without asking any queſtion) into the Counts Chamber. He lay there ready to give up the Ghoſt, deprived of his Senſes, and raving with his tongue. Now he accuſed <hi>Arſinda</hi> as unfaithful and ungrateful; then he condemned himſelf, asking her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as if ſhe had been preſent. No ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had <hi>Arſinda</hi> heard him ſpeak but, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33822:57"/>
ſurpriſed more by wonder or by hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror I know not, ſhe ſwooned away, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her Maiden nor the Counts ſervant being able to ſupport her. The Count on the other ſide, believing <hi>Arſinda</hi> to be a falſe appearance, or elſe the effect of his intenſe deſire and fervent imagination, made no end of weeping and wailing.</p>
               <p>But afterwards, being aſſured that it was <hi>Arſinda</hi> no more angry, nor yet wedd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Marqueſs, his heart was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported with ſo much unexpected joy that, without coming any more to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he breathed out his laſt. This hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Arms of <hi>Arſinda,</hi> whoſe Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had recalled her to life, to reſerve her for a more miſerable death. I want words to expreſs her paſſion. The tearing of her hair, ſcratching of her face, and beating of her breaſt were the weakeſt proofs ſhe gave of her ſorrow. She often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſought for a Knife to kill her ſelf, but was prevented by thoſe that ſtood by her. In this interim came into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Marqueſs <hi>Odorico</hi> who, having notice of her departure, had followed her with an intention to carry her away by force and raviſh her. Scarce did <hi>Arſinda</hi> ſet her eye upon him, but ſhe cryed out,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33822:58"/>
Behold, O wicked man, the triumph of thy perfidiouſneſs. <hi>Odorico,</hi> taking her in his Arms, did endeavour forcibly to remove her from thoſe unhappy objects that did ſo much diſquiet her. But <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinda,</hi> being imboldned by a deſperate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, ſnatched away a Weapon that hung by the Marqueſs his ſide, did give him ſo hearty and fatal a ſtab, that ſhe at once eaſed him both of his love and life. At the ſame time, taking alſo revenge on her ſelf, with a deep wound ſhe opened her own breaſt, making a large paſſage for that ſoul to eſcape thence which was not able to reſiſt the violence of paſſion.</p>
               <p>To ſuch unhappy ends do they come who do not bridle their immoderate affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, nor hearken to reaſon, but, being led away by ſenſuality, do wholly give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to its complacency.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="novel">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:33822:58"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Giacintha</hi> being, in a Dream, enamoured with <hi>Don Pietro de Ponzes,</hi> obliges him to undeceive his Coſen <hi>Leonora</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him for her Husband. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Leonora,</hi> in deſpair, kills her ſelf; having firſt given the Father of <hi>Giacin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cintha</hi> to underſtand the loving intreagues of his Daughter; which makes <hi>Don Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> with his Son <hi>Ardelius,</hi> to purſue <hi>Don Piedro</hi> who, being forced to kill <hi>Ardelius,</hi> flyes into <hi>Flanders. Giaccin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> believing <hi>Don Pietro</hi> to be dead en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into a Nunnery; but ſeeing her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and her Husband both killed by one anothers Sword, ſhe ſuddenly dyeth with grief.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVEL</hi> VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIacintha</hi> was born at <hi>Baeza</hi> a City in <hi>Andaluſia,</hi> having Riches and Nobility well matched to her ſingular Beauty. She was not out of the Cradle when her Mother was laid in the Grave,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33822:59"/>
who left a great Eſtate to be divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt her and her only Brother named <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delius.</hi> Scarce had ſhe attained the age of Fifteen (when many pretenders began to ſue either for her Riches, Beauties, or both) when one night in a Dream, ſhe really lamented the imaginary loſs of her life. She fancied that ſhe ſaw, walking in a very pleaſant Grove, a Man of a more hanſom Garb and Stature than ever ſhe had ſeen before. His face was partly mufled up in his Cloak which, being fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embroidered, did make him look more brave and gallant. <hi>Giacintha</hi> feeling her ſelf toucht with curioſity, had a mind to ſee if his face did correſpond with the other parts of his body, which at firſt ſight, did ſeem to make a moſt admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble compoſure. With a baſhful boldneſs ſhe therefore pulled away that part of his Cloak which he had thrown over his face; but on the contrary it ſeemed that this Man, as a chaſtiſement of her raſhneſs, did, with a Dagger, ſtrike her ſo ſenſibly through the heart, that the pain thereof making her cry out aloud, waked all her ſervants, who preſently ran to her ſuccor, and to free her from thoſe frightful dreams. <hi>Giacintha</hi> was no ſooner deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33822:59"/>
from this repreſentation of danger, but ſhe was poſſeſt with a real affliction of mind, wherein the <hi>idea</hi> of this perſon had made ſuch a deep impreſſion, that no time could poſſibly obliterate it. She de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to encounter with a Man that had thoſe noble and amiable Features, and did let her ſelf be ſo far tranſported by the ſtrength of imagination, that ſhe was in love before ſhe knew with whom. Her flames were increaſed becauſe, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe of them, ſhe could not make the effect to ceaſe. Theſe perplexing thoughts did ſo much diſturb her repoſe that, deſpairing to obtain the love of a Chimera, ſhe was near upon loſing both her health and life. And, in bewailing her ſelf from time to time, ſhe ſpake thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Where is it poſſible to find a more miſerable and unhappy wretch than my ſelf? I love a Dream, and am ready to run mad after a meer fantaſme. I adore a ſhadow, and therefore do excuſe the folly of <hi>Pigmaleon;</hi> and do pity thy dotages O <hi>Xerxes:</hi> Thou lovedſt a Plane-Tree, and the other fell in love with a Statue; yet theſe were bodily ſubſtances that might be both ſeen and felt. If they had no return of love, yet had they poſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſion
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33822:60"/>
of the things beloved. Theſe monſtrous loves gave ſome ſatisfaction to the ſenſes of ſeeing and touching. But my ravings are founded upon an impoſſibility, and have nothing in them more than vain fancy. Shame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion will be the product of my loves which will either not be believed by the World, or elſe will be ſtiled mad and fooliſh. Certainly there is no greater unhappineſs than to adore what cannot be ſeen, and what depends meerly upon nocturnal illuſions. The original of my love ſprings only from fond imagination, neither hath it any other being than a phantome; wherefore I lament and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my ſelf, and I know not for what, nor for whom; I fear that which is not, and I hope for that which is impoſſible.</q>
               </p>
               <p>With theſe paſſionate exhalations <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acintha</hi> did continually perplex her ſelf, when one day, ſtanding in a Balcony, ſhe ſaw a <hi>Cavalier,</hi> in a travelling Habit, going into the next Palace, adjoyning to hers. She, being intenſe upon her thoughts, could not eaſily be diverted by any kind of curioſity; yet letting her eye fall upon the brave Equipage, gallant Train, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preſence of that Gentleman, ſhe knew
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33822:60"/>
him to be the ſame that had wounded her in a dream, and that with abſolute ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny did rule over all the faculties of her ſoul. This was <hi>Don Pietro di Ponzes</hi> a Young Man who, although he had not compleated the fourth luſtre of his Age, yet had with reputation worthily exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all Military Offices, and was returned home to enjoy the honour of them at Court, and to ſee his Father who, being very old, was afraid of dying before he could embrace him. He neither knew, nor was he known by <hi>Giacintha</hi> (though his Siſter <hi>Iſabella</hi> was her great Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) for when <hi>Don Pietro</hi> went for <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> ſhe was but a little Girl. The God of Love brought it ſo about that this young couple did ſacrifice their whole affections unto the Shrine of his Divinity. <hi>Giacintha</hi> was with <hi>Iſabella</hi> to congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the ſafe return of her Brother, who was preſent at this Complement, which made it not difficult for her, by glancing words and eyes, to declare the paſſion of her heart. In brief there paſſed not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days but, by the mediation of <hi>Iſabella,</hi> theſe two Lovers were contracted with a mutual promiſe of Matrimony. But For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune for the moſt part envying the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33822:61"/>
of Lovers order'd the matter ſo that a Coſen of <hi>Don Piedro</hi>'s, called <hi>Leonora,</hi> who was more than hanſom, and extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rich, fell grievouſly in love with him. <hi>Don Piedro</hi> perceived it but, his heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe engaged, made as if he ſaw it not, and that with ſo much cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Leonora</hi> was ready to deſpair. At laſt, ſeeing her ſelf deſpiſed, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not well accepted of, ſhe took to her Bed, leaving the Phyſicians little hopes of her recovery, the wounds of her heart proving to be incurable. The Mother of <hi>Leonora</hi> having the experience of many years, did eaſily know that her Daughters ſickneſs proceeded from love. She there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the help of one of her Maidens, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating into the certainty and original of it, applied her whole endeavours to find out the remedy. She ſends for <hi>Don Piedro</hi> and, in words bedewed with tears and ſighs, ſhe offers him her Daughter, telling him punctually the occaſion of her indiſpoſition. She urged her entreaties by letting him know that he could not meet with a more rich or a more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Match. The Laws of good breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compelled. <hi>Don Piedro</hi> to make a cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous anſwer. And, hoping that the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33822:61"/>
time requiſite for treating and getting the conſent of her friends, might adminiſter ſome cure to this Malady, he remitted the concluſion to the ſole will of his Father, to whom, as his duty was, he entirely referred himſelf. After this he went in to ſee his Coſen, which filled her full of hopes that do eaſily take place in the breaſts of young Virgins. <hi>Leonora</hi> in the mean time, taking courage from the words (tho they were not binding) and continued viſits from <hi>Don Piedro,</hi> in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort time recovered her former health. <hi>Giacintha</hi> on the other ſide, wanting many of his Viſits, did moſt miſerably afflict her ſelf, and frequently inculpate the Loyalty of <hi>Don Pietro.</hi> He, not being able to endure her reſentments, thought of weakning her jealouſie by diſcovering the whole truth unto her. Hereupon <hi>Giacintha</hi> being in a great rage, with a furious tone ſaid unto him. <q>Never ſpeak to me, nor preſume to ſee me more, if you do not make your Kinſwoman know that you are my Spouſe, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hers. Neither my Heart, nor my Honour will ſuffer any Rival.</q> In ſaying ſo ſhe made a motion to be gone, but was ſtopt by <hi>Don Piedro</hi> who, with
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33822:62"/>
horrible imprecations aſſerted his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and promiſed, the next day to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive his Coſen. <hi>Giacintha</hi> being will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to lay a further obligation upon <hi>Don Piedro</hi> for the performance of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, made her ſelf ſure to him by an Oath. <hi>Don Piedro</hi> in theſe delightſome amours having loſt all that circumſpection that before made him cautious, went to ſee his Coſen who, having wholly chaſed away her diſeaſe, was only attending the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect conſummation of her recovery. He was received in the moſt affectionate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that a loving ſoul could put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. But the appearing of ſome trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his looks gave occaſion to <hi>Leonora</hi> to ask him the cauſe of it. After a little ſlight denial <hi>Don Piedro</hi> ſaid, It is not juſtice Madam, that I ſhould betray your good affection, and falſify my own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. My behaviour hath hitherto been rather feigned, than candid. I had a mind to recover you, but I cannot ſatisfie you. Bear with my Fortune that hath obliged me to another. I have paſs'd my word, and am contracted to <hi>Giacintha,</hi> nor can I diſengage my ſelf without loſing my life. 'Tis enough anſwered <hi>Leonora,</hi> yet had you better have letten me dye than
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33822:62"/>
to revive in me the tyranny of paſſion. Patience, the heart that cannot bend may break. Having ſaid this, ſhe went out of the Chamber and retired into a Cloſet, where ſhe let looſe the reins of her anger which thus dictated unto her;
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The injuries that are done to honour do call for revenge even from thoſe that have no intereſt therein. For this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I counſel you to look well to the guard of your Houſe whoſe Honour is endangered by <hi>Don Pietro de Ponzes.</hi> If, blinded by deſtiny, you ſhould think this to be a Forgery, your own eyes, when cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, will give you teſtimony of the truth hereof.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>She ſealed the Letter without ſubſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and ſent it by a Footman belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Father of <hi>Giacintha.</hi> This done ſhe returned into her Cloſet for to write another, while <hi>Don Pietro,</hi> being doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful what reſolutions an incenſed Woman might take, made haſte away. Afterwards <hi>Leonora</hi> went out of the Cloſet to her Mother, begging her Bleſſing for that ſhe was afraid ſhe ſhould never ſee her more.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33822:63"/>
Her Mother chid her, ſaying. <hi>O Daughter, do not uſe theſe hateful expreſſions to me, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you intend to ſhorten my days. Leonora</hi> with tears in her eyes left her Mother. She had not gone far but, ſending forth a deep ſigh, ſhe fell down dead. All the Houſe ran to her ſuccour and, believing her to be only in a Swoon, they applied all things proper to bring her to her ſelf again. All their endeavours were in vain, and the Doctor being come knew her to be dead indeed. In ſtripping off her Cloths there fell from her Boſom a Letter which, being directed to her Mother, ſpake thus:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Dear Mother,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I my ſelf have undertaken to chaſtiſe the intemperance of my ſenſual appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, by taking Poiſon to expel my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate affection. I thought Death would be more pleaſing to me, than to ſee my Coſen in the Arms of another Woman. I beſeech you pardon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure which this my reſolution ſhall have given you, by judging it neceſſary to terminate the diſquiet of my heart. <hi>Adieu,</hi> deareſt Mother, <hi>adieu.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your unfortunate <hi>Leonora.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:33822:63"/>This unhappy accident occaſioned great diſturbance in the minds of her Mother and Kindred, and ſome there were, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with her Love-affair, that did ſo far err in their judgment, as to impute this her ſudden death unto her great riches. <hi>Giacintha</hi> knowing her ſelf to be unwillingly guilty of this Woman-ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, had a mind to have ſome affectionate diſcourſe about it with <hi>Don Pietro.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe ſends privately to tell him, that ſhe deſired to ſee him that very night. <hi>Don Pietro</hi> went accordingly and was, as at other times, conducted into a low Chamber, by a ſervant, who afterwards ſtood as Sentinel at the Door. <hi>Giaccin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> was ſcarce come into the room, when <hi>Don Garzia,</hi> who by the Letter that did tax his honour was made very vigilant, was at the apartment of his Daughter. But not finding her there, he went on to that of his Son, where they both armed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for to revenge the affront done unto their Reputation. They could not do this ſo ſilently but that ſome of the Servants gave notice thereof to the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, who thereby had the opportunity of getting away before they were aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Don Pietro</hi> carried <hi>Giacintha</hi> to an
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33822:64"/>
Aunt of hers in a Monaſtery; and he, by retiring, ſecured himſelf from the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution which he feared, of Juſtice. <hi>Don Garzia,</hi> being wounded in the moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible part of his Soul, did fully reſolve to revenge, this diſgrace by himſelf. He was ſo far from preferring his complaints to the Judges, that he ſeemed not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the leaſt ſenſe of this injury. He anſwered thoſe that ſpoke to him of it in ſuch a manner that did rather favour of ſtolidity than of revenge.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs <hi>Don Pietro</hi> was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his due circumſpection, hoping at length by Marrying <hi>Giacintha,</hi> by exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing acts of modeſty, and by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of time to appeaſe the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable rage of <hi>Don Garzia.</hi> In the mean time, to ſhelter himſelf from Juſtice, he took Sanctuary in a little Grove be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to a <hi>Nunnery,</hi> where he ſtaid the longer, becauſe in the night time, by means of the Gardner, he had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of diſcourſing with <hi>Giacintha</hi> through an iron-barred Window. <hi>Don Garzia,</hi> having intimation hereof, got admittance one Night, by the mediation of Gold, and with Sword in Hand, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his Son, ſet upon <hi>Don Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro.</hi>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33822:64"/>
He, fearing to violate the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> and unwilling to hazard the lives of his intended Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Brother-in-law, betook himſelf to flight. He was hotly purſued by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delius;</hi> wherefore to ſtop his fury, and ſave himſelf, <hi>Don Piedro</hi> facing about, was forced to run him into the ſide. <hi>Arde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> thereupon ſuddenly fell down, his Soul, together with his Bloud, expiring in the ſame moment, <hi>Don Garzia</hi> could not come up time enough either to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour his Son, or apprehend his enemy. The daylight, diſcovering this ſad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, raiſed up great murmurings, in ſo much as <hi>Don Piedro,</hi> having privately ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken leave of <hi>Giacintha,</hi> for to ſecure himſelf, departed for <hi>Flanders,</hi> which is the <hi>Aſylum</hi> of all wicked and unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate men. <hi>Don Garzia,</hi> not being able, at preſent, to ſacrifice the bloud of <hi>Don Piedro</hi> to his revenge, went about to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviate his ſorrow by tormenting the ſoul of <hi>Giacintha.</hi> He therefore, being very laviſh of his Gold, to bring this to effect, contrived it ſo that all the Letters of <hi>Don Piedro</hi> were brought to his hands. There was a Month paſt wherein <hi>Giacin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> was tortured with the impatience of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33822:65"/>
hearing from <hi>Don Piedro,</hi> when one day, being at the Window with her Husband's Father, ſhe took ſome comfort in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her a Letter which came from <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellona,</hi> whither <hi>Don Piedro</hi> went deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thence for <hi>Naples,</hi> and ſo for <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> She having haſtily unfolded the Letter found what followeth:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>'Tis not without extream and hearty ſorrow, that I ſend you the unhappy News of the loſs of your Son <hi>Signor Don Piedro.</hi> He going late out of a Gaming-houſe laſt Night was killed by many Wounds he received in his Breaſt; no body knowing, nor ſo much as ſuſpecting who ſhould be the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors. It grieves me that I ſhould write you ſo ungrateful a Letter, but my affection and obligation could not exempt me from this Office. To mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row he will be buried with that Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that is due to his Birth and my grief. I pray God in his Mercy to moderate your affliction, and to give you that conſolation which ſuch an unlucky and cruel chance doth deſerve. You ſhall be informed of his concerns
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33822:65"/>
by a better opportunity, in the mean time pleaſe to know that I am</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt devoted ſervant <hi>Il Capitan Diego di Mara.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>This Captain was an intimate friend of <hi>Don Pietro</hi>'s who went with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Flanders.</hi> But the Letter was forg'd by <hi>Don Garzia,</hi> not only to triumph in the grief of <hi>Giacintha,</hi> but alſo to divert her correſpondence with <hi>Don Piedro;</hi> and it ſucceeded as he would have it. For <hi>Don Piedro,</hi> coming unto <hi>Naples,</hi> and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Letters neither from <hi>Giacintha,</hi> nor his Father, according as they had agreed, without ſtaying long, embarqued for <hi>Flanders.</hi> There, for diverſion of his troubled thoughts, he betook himſelf to Gaming and Courting of Women, in ſuch manner, that for Six Years time he neither regarded his Spouſe, nor his Country. In this <hi>interim</hi> the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Giacintha</hi> being drowned in tears, and believing that the advice of <hi>Don Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro</hi>'s Death was true, made her tender affection ſubmit to hard neceſſity, by
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33822:66"/>
liſting her ſelf a Nun in the ſame <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery</hi> where ſhe had taken refuge. Here, truly humbling her ſelf, ſhe led a life more Divine than Humane. <hi>Don Piedro,</hi> on the other hand, being ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited with the love of many, fixed his whole delight upon one only Woman who, being either more fair or more cunning than the reſt, had made her ſelf abſolute Miſtreſs of his Heart. While thus <hi>Don Piedro</hi> thought of bringing his amorous hopes to perfection, he ſaw them all blaſted in the wilful reſolution of his beloved who ſent him this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Signor Don Piedro,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Your pretenſions are very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome unto me. My free choice and my Deſtiny do both forbid me to be yours, I being already eſpouſed to the <hi>Count Aurelius.</hi> And although my heart ſhall alway preſerve indelible the memory of your kind expreſſions; yet I would not have you, by this declaration, to bring the leaſt prejudice upon my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, or my Husband's Reputation. Be
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33822:66"/>
pleas'd to accept of this acknowledgment, which is all you can expect from</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obliged Servant <hi>Anna Maria.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>This Paper did raiſe up the ſpirits of <hi>Don Piedro</hi> to ſuch a pitch that he was, for ſome little time, beſide himſelf. At length, coming to himſelf again, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that he could not better heal this latter Wound of Love, than by opening the former, he returned back to <hi>Barza.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before he ſaw his own Houſe he went to the <hi>Nunnery</hi> to ſee <hi>Giacintha.</hi> Under pretence of bringing her ſome Letters from <hi>Flanders,</hi> he made her be called and, giving her to underſtand that he was <hi>Don Piedro,</hi> he cauſed ſuch a ſudden change in her that ſhe was ready to have fainted away. <hi>Giacintha,</hi> recovering this oppreſſion of Spirit, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by ſuch ſurprizing joy, did preſently revive her former affection, which became the more ardent for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuppreſt by the tye of Religion.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33822:67"/>
Yet this pair of Lovers thought it not difficult to obtain a Diſpenſation; ſince that the Bond of Matrimony did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eede that of Devotion, and <hi>Giacintha</hi> was no more at her own diſpoſal, for that ſhe had taken upon her a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Habit, ſuppoſing her ſelf to be freed from the obligation of Marriage by the pretended death of <hi>Don Piedro.</hi> They were contriving to bring about their amorous deſires to a ſucceſsful end, when <hi>Don Garzia,</hi> being informed of <hi>Don Peedro</hi>'s return, and of the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments he had with his Daughter, thought he had offended the Courage of his Mind by ſo long forbearance. And, aſpiring to waſh off the Stains of his Reputation by a bloudy revenge; being full of rancour, he ran to the Grates of the Monaſtery. There he found his Daughter having her hands between thoſe of <hi>Don Piedro,</hi> and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a very ſtrict conference with him. His defiance, threatning, laying hand on his Sword, and mortally wounding of <hi>Don Piedro</hi> was all done in a trice. <hi>Don Garzia</hi> would in like manner have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed his fury upon <hi>Giacintha</hi> if he had not been prevented by <hi>Don Piedro</hi> who,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33822:67"/>
ſtrugling with approaching death, did ſo much reinforce himſelf as that, either to ſave his Beloved, or revenge himſelf, he ſtruck <hi>Don Garzia</hi> with a Dagger to the heart. <hi>Don Garzia</hi> fell down dead; and at the ſame time <hi>Don Piedro</hi> alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily left this life. <hi>Giacintha,</hi> at ſo dolorous a Spectacle, ſtood like a Stock. Tears, which do uſually, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, aſſwage grief, in her did augment it. Words, which by their expreſſion do commonly make ſorrow more ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, in her, by the greatneſs of the miſchief, were ſtifled before they could be uttered. Her eyes therefore not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to behold ſo diſmal a Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and her heart not being ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to reſiſt ſuch cruel tortures, which rob'd her in the ſame moment, both of her Father and Husband, ſeeing her loſſes to be deſperate and irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, being overcome by deadly grief, ſhe fell down to the ground, and unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately gave up the Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>By this it appears, that Women, in pleaſing the inordinate appetites of their Senſes, and in diſobeying the Will and Commands of their Parents, do often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33822:68"/>
prepare a funeral for their own, and others happineſs: and that Men, by ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Punctilio's of Honour, and by exerciſing the deſires of revenge, do ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine the greatneſs of their Families, and leave behind them an unhappy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored memory to Poſterity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="novel">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:33822:68"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Diego Saranda,</hi> being diſguſted by a certain Lady, reſolves to love no more; and therefore makes it his buſineſs to rail againſt Women. Which being reproved in him by <hi>Iſabella</hi> he falls in love with her. And having receiv'd two kind invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come to her Houſe, is diverted by ſome accidents of Fire and Sword. So that, being fearful of hazarding any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his life, he intends to quit the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize: but, being again encouraged by <hi>Iſabella,</hi> he is admitted into her Bed. Where a new occaſion of diſguſt ariſing, he departs without enjoying her.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>NOVEL</hi> IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DOn Diego di Saranda,</hi> a Gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leman of excellent Merit and Vertue, coming to <hi>Genoua,</hi> and taking a private Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where he might leaſt be known, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to evaporate his paſſionate Invectives
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33822:69"/>
in this manner. He that builds his hopes upon the hearts and promiſes of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may boaſt of a foundation more unſtable than the Waves. <hi>Woman,</hi> he that had the wit to call thee <hi>Woe man</hi> did deſcribe but a little part of thy nature. For the precipices of thy inconſtancy, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiety of thy affections, and the Helliſh torments that thou makeſt thy Lovers to endure, cannot be comprehended in the ſingle word <hi>Woe.</hi> He that called thee Heaven, had regard perhaps to thy Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and malign influences. And who ſo idolizes thee with the name of Deity, does it more in contemplation of the pride of thy Sex, and the folly of men, than of any deſert of thine. The Aſtrologers had great reaſon to make the Houſe of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men common with that of domeſtick enemies, and to place the Houſe of Death near to that of a Wife: for you betray with your ſmiles, entrap by your tears, and kill with your wantonneſs.</p>
               <p>Enough, no more, <hi>Signor Don Diego,</hi> for God's ſake, replied a Lady, interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, that was very well known unto him, whom we, out of reſpect to her Quality, will call by the borrowed name of <hi>Iſabella.</hi> It misbecomes all men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:33822:69"/>
ſhe, to reproach the Female Sex, which, though naturally it be more weak, yet is it more noble than that of yours. He that rails at Woman-kind, either doth not know their Merit, or is unworthy to be acquainted with it. Gentlemen, like you, ought to draw their Swords againſt thoſe that ſcandalize Women, and not to arm their tongues with injurious words againſt the reputation of thoſe who have contributed to their Being.</p>
               <p>Madam, anſwered <hi>Don Diego,</hi> my grief tyrannizing over my tongue, hath made me utter ſome odd conceits which though they are the product of anger, yet are they not the offspring of falſhood: But I neither can, nor will diſpute this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with you, becauſe neither my mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, nor the reſpect I owe you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it. But if you had had that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a man, that I have met with in a Woman, ſure I am you would wiſh for a tongue of Thunder and Lightning that might ſtrike dead and reduce all Mankind into Aſhes; and would exclaim againſt Dame Nature for neceſſitating you to obey ſo odious a ſubject.</p>
               <p>Tell me, I pray you (ſaid <hi>Iſabella</hi> again) the injury that hath thus excited
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33822:70"/>
your hatred againſt Women. Certainly it ought to be very great ſeeing it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torts from you revenge even againſt thoſe alſo that have not in the leaſt offended you.</p>
               <p>In anſwer to this <hi>Don Diego</hi> ſays, I will give you a brief relation of my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous adventures, becauſe I am ſure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to obtain both compaſſion to my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, and excuſe for my hatred againſt Women. It is now almoſt five years ſince I firſt dedicated my affection unto a certain beautiful and noble Lady. This Lady ſeeming to accept of my love, made me ſo proud that I ſcornfully deſpiſed all other amours; and you, Madam, can be my witneſs herein, ſeeing I continually refuſed the favour of your love, declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that my ambition was rather to lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh for the love of one, than to enjoy the correſpondence of a thouſand others. Seeing that my moſt humble ſervice was not unpleaſing to her, after a long and faithful attendance I ſued for the reward unto which Lovers do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly aſpire. There followed many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays masked under the pretences of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Caution, when no longer ago than yeſterday, I received a challenge to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:33822:70"/>
meet my ſweet Miſtreſs, at night in <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> field. I am not able to tell you my unſpeakable conſolation. I as earneſtly deſired the ſetting of the Sun, as Batts and Owls do deſire darkneſs. I came to the appointed place and gave the ſign preſcribed me; but was anſwered by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but mocks and ſcoffs, upbraiding my credulity in believing that a Lady of her eſteem ſhould proſtrate her Honour to a Lover; and yet, with theſe eyes, I beheld her Gallant triumphing in my ſcorn, and, with his arms about her Neck, deriding my Love and Conſtancy. <hi>Don Diego</hi> did aggravate theſe paſſages with ſo much paſſion, that <hi>Iſabella,</hi> taking pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of him, broke off his Story ſaying. And now <hi>Signor Don Diego,</hi> why do you blame the Female Sex if, by the ill plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your affections, you have met with deriſion inſtead of reward? You ſhould lay the blame on her that offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, and not include in a particular injury a general revenge againſt thoſe that are innocent. Without doubt you are wholly in the fault who, by neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the advantages offered you, have indiſcreetly fled from her that loved you, and blindly purſued her that hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33822:71"/>
you. This <hi>Don Diego</hi> is a Judgment from Heaven. Acknowledge it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, for it is always good to change Counſels, when you may reap profit thereby. I am the ſame that ever I was, and as I have long ſet a great value upon your merit; ſo I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour all I can to recompence it.</p>
               <p>If I did believe, anſwered <hi>Don Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ego,</hi> that my blind conſtancy did not make me unworthy of your favour, I would muſter up all my Spirits, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice the whole ſtrength of my heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Beauty; and by my paſt ardors you may gueſs how fervent my future love will he.</p>
               <p>'Tis enough, <hi>Don Diego,</hi> reply'd <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella.</hi> I am yours, and you ſhall always find me ſo. Your paſt averſion hath but refin'd my affection. If this Night you will put on the Habit of a Gardner, and come to my Houſe, I will make you to know that Women are not at all blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; and that the defect is in Men who love without diſtinction, as being guided more by Paſſion than Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Having thus ſpoken, ſhe left <hi>Don Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ego,</hi> I know not whether more joyful
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33822:71"/>
of his new Adventure, or fearful of ſome new misfortune. For, calling to mind his late ſlighting of this Lady, he thought it impoſſible ſhe ſhould preſerve ſo much kindneſs for him as that, inſtead of revenge, ſhe ſhould beſtow upon him thoſe favours, which are the the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of long and faithful ſervices, and a loving correſpondence. But his ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al appetite prevailing above all other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, he went, as ſoon as 'twas Night, to the Houſe of <hi>Iſabella.</hi> She received him moſt affectionately, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards conducted him, unſeen, into a Ground-room which, by a back pair of Stairs, did lead into her own Chamber. Here ſhe pray'd him to diſpence with ſtaying a little, till her Maidens (who were naturally prying into theſe kind of ſecrets) being retired, might give a better opportunity for their amorous Thefts. After this <hi>Iſabella,</hi> thinking it long e'er ſhe were with <hi>Don Diego,</hi> feigned her ſelf not very well, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe diſmiſſed her Servants, and allowed ſome time for their going to ſleep. In the mean time <hi>Don Diego,</hi> thinking every moment that did delay his ſatisfaction to be very tedious, did
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:33822:72"/>
believe that he was betrayed. He ſaw the Room, where he was, beſieged by enrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flames; and it ſeemed to him that the Fire did upbraid his incontinency and, by the purity of its ardor, threaten to extinguiſh the impurity of his deſires And the rather, for that there came in to his mind the paſt ill opinions he had of Women, and he perſwaded himſelf that this was a trick put upon him by <hi>Iſabella,</hi> which indeed was but a meer accident. The Servants had careleſly left fire in the next Room which, having lain hid a Day and a Night, broke out with ſo much fury that the poor lover was near being ſacrificed. He would have cried out, but he durſt not for fear (being found in that place) of being kill'd either as a Thief or an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer. He tryed to get out but could not, <hi>Iſabella</hi> having ſecured him by faſt locking of the Door. His fear was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by the confuſed noiſe of thoſe in the Houſe who cryed out Fire, Fire, and hearing them already ask for the Key of his Chamber, he knew not what excuſe to make to thoſe that ſhould find him there. But his danger did not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of long conſultation, ſince he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33822:72"/>
began to feel the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the elementary and imaginary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lames. In theſe ſtreights he heard a little Door opening into the Room which he had not till then obſerved. And now he gave himſelf for loſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng he could not on the ſudden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think himſelf of any pretence that might ſerve to cover his guiltineſs. He was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſome meaſure refreſhed by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng of <hi>Iſabella</hi> who, taking him by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and, haſtily drew him (trembling) out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the ſame private way that he went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, ſaying to him, <hi>Don Diego</hi> you are very unfortunate in your amours, ſeeing that the Houſe is on fire. I do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow wonder at other Women for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refuſed you. Get you among the Crowd of thoſe that run to the fire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ſo you may go away uneſpied; and we will order our buſineſs better for the future. This ſucceeded happily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Don Diego;</hi> for he, making as if he were drawn thither by the noiſe, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put off the Gardners Coat, did manfully aſſiſt in putting out the fire, which without his help would certainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave dilated its Violences much farther. After this he received publick Thanks
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33822:73"/>
from <hi>Iſabella</hi> who, in very affectionate and reſpectful terms, did expreſs he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own Gratitude, and her Husbands ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation unto him. <hi>Don Diego</hi> departe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more enamoured than before, his inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affection gaining ſtrength by this accidental oppoſition; ſo that he continued to give freſh teſtimonies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his reſpects towards <hi>Iſabella</hi> who, being deſirous to bring her amorous practice to perfection, ſent him the following Letter:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Dear,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>It behoved me to moderate the arden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of my affection in the preſence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> my Husband. He is newly gone into the Country, and I do in this Paper en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe my heart to you. If the Fire o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> our Houſe hath not extinguiſhed tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of your Breaſt I ſhall expect you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Third Hour of the Night. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> deſire that you would diſguiſe you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf under the Habit of <hi>Auſtin</hi> my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and ſo by help of the Ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> herewith ſent you, you may enter th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Houſe without any the leaſt ſuſpicion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           <pb n="143" facs="tcp:33822:73"/>
In the mean time pleaſe to accept of her Services who profeſſes her ſelf to be</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt devoted and obliged Servant. <hi>Iſabella.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego,</hi> upon the receipt of this Letter, thought himſelf in Heaven; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his reading and kiſſing it over and over, and the putting of it up in his Boſom were the leaſt demonſtrations of his joyful affection. After this, taking Pen and Paper, he ſent this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My dear heart,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I, being equally confounded by the greatneſs of your favour, and the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my deſert, cannot tell how to expreſs my obligations. I will come, in the ſilent time of the Night, and ſacrifice my heart unto you. I have nothing more valuable, nor more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to my deſire, and Love it
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:33822:74"/>
ſelf pretends to no more. It is great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that I ſhould transform my ſelf into the likeneſs of what I ſhall always be,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt obliged Servant <hi>Don Diego.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>At length the Night came that was ſo often called upon by him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, in the Diſguiſe, and at the hour appointed he went to the Houſe of <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella.</hi> He was near opening the Door when he ſaw himſelf aſſaulted by four Men who, with Cudgels in their hands, began to bang him ſoundly. Theſe were ſome debauched Youths who, having been affronted (as they pretended) by <hi>Auſtin,</hi> did there lye in wait to beat him, and taking <hi>Don Diego,</hi> by his Clothes, to be <hi>Auſtin,</hi> they did ſorely rib-baſte him. <hi>Don Diego,</hi> not being us'd to take blows, drew out a Piſtol, and, diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, lightly wounded one of them in the ſide. He would have returned his ſalute with a kind of ſhort Gun which, if it had taken fire, would certainly have cooled <hi>Don Diego</hi>'s hot deſire. The reſt
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33822:74"/>
of the aggreſſors did likewiſe diſcharge their Piſtols at <hi>Don Diego</hi> but, by great chance, none of them did hit him. Yet he had fallen a Sacrifice to their anger (for they had all thrown away their Sticks and drawn their Swords) if <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella,</hi> crying aloud out at a Window, had not haſtned all the men in her Houſe to ſuccour him that was aſſaulted; whereupon theſe young Men, fearing to be known and not being willing to venture any further, ran all away, and gave <hi>Don Diego</hi> the opportunity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring, who, being unwilling that the pleaſures of his Senſe ſhould any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger triumph in the dangers of his life, wrote to <hi>Iſabella</hi> as followeth:
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Fortune having always been my Foe, doth oblige me to take new mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, unleſs I ſhould have a mind un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately to end my days. He that will not take warning from Fire and Sword deſerves to be deſtroyed by Thunder, which my raſhneſs is not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33822:75"/>
ſo forward as to provoke; nor do I ſuppoſe that your Love would have me ſubjected to the Wrath of Heaven. And as I ſhall always rejoice in the thoughts of being your ſervant, ſo I will never cancel the obligation you have laid upon me. Do not condemn (O Fair Lady) that heart which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is humane, is awfully over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by Divine Prodigies. To rebel againſt the Government of Heaven is not proper for one that is a Slave to Love, and that thinks his happineſs depends upon the Starry influence of his Miſtreſſes eyes. Yet, in my heart, I will unalterably preſerve the great eſteem I have for your Merit, and the favour ſhewed to</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt obliged and moſt faithful Servant <hi>D. Diego.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the receit of this Letter <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella</hi> ſaw that her hopes were turning into deſpair. She knew that Carnal Appetites grew more violent for being
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:33822:75"/>
interrupted, wherefore ſhe believed that the excuſes of <hi>Don Diego</hi> proceeded ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from want of love, than for fear. At length ſhe returned him this following medley of Love, Jealouſie, Anger and Reproof, <hi>Viz.</hi>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>'Tis no wonder that you meet with ſuch ill ſucceſs in your Amours, ſince that Fortune hates the puſillanimous, and loves the couragious. The enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Love are not attained to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out labour and danger. He that prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticates evil to himſelf deſerves to have it; and the fear of Predictions doth often facilitate their acceſs. Yet I, who am acquainted with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity of your heart, and the greatneſs of your Spirit, cannot think you will be frighted at Chimera's and Bug-Bears which do frighten (and that but ſeldom too) none but Women and Children. He is no true Lover that can change at every Chance; and it argues a debaſed mind to be eaſily overcome
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33822:76"/>
by difficulties. But your Valour may be abuſed by the encouragement of a Woman, who though her Sex be weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet her Love is ſtronger than yours.</p>
                        <p>This Evening by means of the Revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings that are to be at my Houſe, you may go into my Chamber, and ſhut your ſelf in the Cloſet which you will find left open for that purpoſe. I hope this Night to make you know that the ſoft pleaſures of Love are ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by hazards and hardſhips. In the mean time preſerve me as I am</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt cordial Lover and Servant <hi>Iſabella.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>In reading of this Letter <hi>Don Diego</hi> felt in himſelf a great conturbation of Spirit. The Beautys of <hi>Iſabella</hi> which, by gentle reproofs, did ſue for his Love, did make the greateſt danger ſeem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible unto him; but the acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal encounters of Fire and Sword did confirm in him his reflections on Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Prudence. At laſt, Sence got
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33822:76"/>
the upper hand, and made him reſolve that, poſtponing all other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he would for the ſake of <hi>Iſabella,</hi> and to pleaſe his own inclinations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf to the moſt imminent pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils. And though his mind miſgave him, promiſing him no good effect in this Affair; yet he was reſolute in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it, and went and ſhut himſelf unſeen, into <hi>Iſabellas</hi> Cloſet. Here he ſtay'd a long time, expecting her with extraordinary impatience, and did often reprove or approve his deſign, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the various dictates of Senſe and Reaſon. After a great while <hi>Iſabella</hi> came and, with a multitude of ſweet Kiſſes, raviſhed the heart of <hi>Don Diego,</hi> in ſuch ſort that, being intoxicated with theſe delicious endearments, he clear for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got all his paſt misfortunes. <hi>Iſabella</hi> for to attain the deſired end of all Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, began to undreſs, deſiring <hi>Don Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ego</hi> to do the like. He, in obeying her, pray'd her to ſhut the Chamber-door, that none of her Maidens, who are wont to watch over their Miſtreſſes actions, might perceive them. Let me alone for that, ſaid <hi>Iſabella,</hi> you are a very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:33822:77"/>
and fearful Lover. I, that hazard my Life, my Eſtate, and my good Name, do think of nothing but of ſerving you, and you, by needleſs cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpections, do imbitter the ſweetneſs of our affections. I ſee how pure your Love is, that hath a mixture of ſo much fear. <hi>Don Diego</hi> bluſht at theſe words and, without reply, ſtripping all off, he went into Bed.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time <hi>Iſabella</hi> had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe put off her Cloaths, but inſtead of running into the Embraces of <hi>Don Diego,</hi> who lay with open arms impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently expecting her, ſhe went to a little Side-Table, for to ſet up and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate a Mouſe-Trapp. And were it either for making too much haſte, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe that happened amiſs, ſhe let the wyer that held up the trap fall ſeveral times from her hand. <hi>Don Diego</hi>'s Patience being worn out in attendance, and fearing that ſome Servant might come at the clattering of that noiſe, ſaid, Madam, what are you doing? Why do you ſpend ſo much precious time in vain? Are thoſe amorous deſires cooled that were ſo ardent in you a little while ago?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:33822:77"/>To which <hi>Iſabella</hi> anſwered, My Dear, who ſo is not a true Enemy, cannot be a true Friend. I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge me of a certain Mouſe that has done me a thouſand injuries; and more eſpecially the laſt Night did gnaw me a Peach which for its goodlineſs, and for the Perſons ſake that gave it was much valued by me.</p>
               <p>Why then, replied <hi>Don Diego,</hi> will you let a Lover languiſh while you take revenge of a poor Mouſe? Pray lay aſide revenging, and let us fall to lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And then again he renewed his inſtances, that ſhe would leave the Trap, and come to Bed.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Iſabella</hi> being obſtinate, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as if ſhe did not hear him, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came highly incenſed. Whereupon his paſſed fears being awakened, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo afraid that the Noiſe might call ſome of her Servants thither, he ſaid,
<floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Madam Iſabella,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Since that you had rather entrap a
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:33822:78"/>
ſilly Mouſe, than oblige a Lover; I alſo will now let my Reaſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail over my Senſe, and will no longer beſtow my affection upon one who prefers an inconſiderable Revenge  before it.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Whereunto <hi>Iſabella</hi> anſwering no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, he, haſtily putting on ſome, and making a bundle of the reſt of his Clothes, departed the Chamber, and ſo went out of the Houſe, looking after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon <hi>Iſabella</hi> with a very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Eye. She therefore either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing this his reſolution, or recanting the too much indulgence of her own inclination, cared no more for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:33822:78"/>Such is the mutability of humane affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Whereupon we may conclude that the minds of Women are many times in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, and ſometimes overcome by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoneſty and revenge: and that no wiſe men ought ever to adventure their Lives in the vain purſuit of unlawful pleaſures, or ſenſual enjoyments.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
